<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Erastus, or, The Roman prince being a more full acount of that famous history of the seven wise masters : with many pleasant additions of excellent, and divertive discourses, and songs, not unsuitable to the design of the story.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31439</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11980065</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11980065</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1008:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Erastus, or, The Roman prince being a more full acount of that famous history of the seven wise masters : with many pleasant additions of excellent, and divertive discourses, and songs, not unsuitable to the design of the story.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 152 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman ... and Benj. Alsop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Illustrated added t.p.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Seven wise masters.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Classical literature.</term>
               <term>Latin literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51812:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here his arraignd unjustly you may see:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE HISTORY OF <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> And The Seven Wiſe Maſters OF ROME.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aphro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icia: Erastus</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>engraved title page</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51812:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ERAST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S:</hi> OR, THE <hi>Roman Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING A more full Account of that Famous HISTORY OF THE Seven Wiſe MASTERS.</p>
            <p>WITH Many Pleaſant Additions of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and Divertive Diſcourſes, and Songs, not unſuitable to the Deſign of the Story.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>Kings Armes,</hi> and <hi>Benj. Alſop</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51812:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51812:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe Hiſtory of <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> or the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Prince,</hi> hath Juſtly obtained a great eſteem amongſt men; For whereas other Works of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tend to the depraving and Corrupting the tender Inclinations of Youth, we find the deſign of this to be the Promotion, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of Virtue, and Ingenuity. What Fortitude and Conſtancy? What Patience and Humility is there not Conſpicuous in the whole Series of <hi>Eraſtus's</hi> Life? We ſee him one day the Minion, and Darling of Fortune, courted with all the Favours of a Prodigal and Exceſſive Bounty: Another time, we have him toſt and hurried by the Black Tempeſt of Adverſity, on the Rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Rocks of Envy, Diſtruſt and Inhumane Malice. One day the Object of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Care and Affection, the next of his Rage and Contempt. Such is the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of Sublunary Eſtates, and Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! That for the firſt and ſecond Scean of this Princes Life, he ſeemed to be one
<pb facs="tcp:51812:3"/> of the Ludibria Fortune, a meer Tennis Ball of the Blind Goddeſs: But then if we obſerve the equallity of his Temper, his Conſtancy to himſelf, and Virtue, under all thoſe direful Circumſtances; we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him one deſtinated by the Gods to be a Preſident of a Victorious Virtue and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity. For the Latter Scenes of his Life, they ſeem to Import that happy and Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Condition which Heaven appoints as a reward to a Philoſophical and Manly For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and looks like the Glorious, and All-enlivening beams of <hi>Apollo</hi> after he has chaſed away the ſhades of the Cold Noctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Nymph, and made the Morning ſmile with the Welcom approach of his Amorous heat.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Eraſtus</hi> anſwers the Character of a Heroick and brave Man; ſo have you in <hi>Diocleſian</hi> an Emblem of as great Inconſtancy, and ſoft Efeminacy; and yet not altogether without ſome good Impreſſions, whileſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hamering of Reaſon, and ſage Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; but ſoon deluded with falſe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and violently hurried by Inordinate Appetite, and unruly Paſſion; ſtill taken up with the next Plauſible Object, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering any Congruity of Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>In the Seven Maſters, you have the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a true and Sincere Friendſhip,
<pb facs="tcp:51812:3"/> and a conſtant and inviolable Adheſion to the Truth, which is indeed one of the beſt Figures in the make of a Wiſe Man. Some will have theſe Seven Maſters to be the Seven Liberal Sciences, which if a Man be throughly acquainted and inſtructed withal in his Youth, they will be conſtant helps to him in Adverſity, and the beſt of his Ornaments in a Proſperous State.</p>
            <p>Under the Notion of the Empreſs, you have the Deſcription of a Venomous, and Implacable Mallice, Covered over with all the Artifices of Deceit. She enters into a League and Contract with Hell; ſets up the moſt Diabolical Reſolutions in the World, and purſues them with as much fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſubtilty as the Devil himſelf could do. What did ſhe not Feign? What not Attempt againſt the Life of the Innocent <hi>Eraſtus?</hi> How often had ſhe Impoſed upon the too Credulous <hi>Diocleſian</hi> to his own Deſtruction. Take a ſurvey of all the Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Cruelties, Frauds, and Treacheries that ever were in that Deceitful and Deceptible part of that <hi>Sex,</hi> and you will ſee the Wife of <hi>Diocleſian</hi> crawling all over with that ſort of Vermin; ſo that you may well conclude it was impoſſible for Woman to render her ſelf more infamous. Then you have the natural Conſequence of all her Villany; ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:51812:4"/> was (after all her ſhams) Detected, Reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Deſpiſed: She became Nauſeous to others, Loathſom to her ſelf; weary of her wretched Life, and Dyed rather Obſtinate than Penitent.</p>
            <p>Thus have I in brief Opened and Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the deſign of the Following Story; but you will find it much enlarged, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhed with great Variety of Additions, for the Delight, as well as Profit of the Reader. Many Songs are incerted that are not unſuitable to the Purpoſe, and I may without Vanity tell the Reader, that the <hi>Roman Prince</hi> never yet appeared in a Dreſs ſo agreeable to his Quality. I have made way for another Volumn to Compleat the Story of <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> which (if the Reader kindly accept of my Poor Endeavours in this) I ſhall be much Incouraged to Publiſh.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51812:4"/>
            <head>THE Seven Wiſe MASTERS: Or, The Delectable HISTORY OF <hi>Prince Eraſtus.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The Emperor <hi>Diocleſian</hi> chuſeth Seven Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers to Inſtruct his Son <hi>Eraſtus</hi> in the Liberal Sciences. The Death of the Empreſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne thouſand and forty Years after <hi>Romulus</hi> had laid the Foundation of that once fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City of <hi>Rome,</hi> there Raigned the Renowned Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Diocleſian;</hi> the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of whoſe Wiſdom and Greatneſs ſtretched far beyond the Confines of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51812:5"/> own vaſt Empire. This Monarch having been Married to a Princeſs, no leſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous for Beauty and Extraction, had their Nuptials crowned with the Birth of a Son, whoſe excellent ſhape, and fair out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide beſpake the unparalleld perfection of its Inhabitant, which at his firſt appearance ſeemed to be born for the Grandure of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and looked more like an off-ſpring of the Gods, than any thing of human Race, which gave the occaſion of his name <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> (that is to ſay) Amiable or Lovely. This was confirmed by the Nativity-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and Magicians of that Age, who by their Schemes had given the Emperor an account of what he was to hope from a Child, born under ſuch fortunate Configu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Which made the Parent ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to Seaſon his very Infancy with the beſt principles for the Enobling of his High Birth; wherefore he choſe him Tutors, to the Number of the Grecian <hi>Sages,</hi> which were Seven; and proportionable to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Arts: Theſe having withdrawn him to a Princely Manſion near the City, where both privacy and delight contributed to the furtherance of his Studies: For the ſhady Groves, the pleaſant Walks, the warbling Birds, the chriſtal Streams, and ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Palace, proclaimed the Delicacy of this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51812:5"/> ſwéet Retreat. So that at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Age of ten years, this Royal Pupil diſcovered a great profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience in <hi>Grammar, Logick, Geography,</hi> and the other Sciences, to the Aſtoniſhment of the Philoſophers themſelves, who were ſtruck with Wonder, both at the Growth and Beauty of his outward Form; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially his vaſt Improvement in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Philoſophy. And now, as a Trial of this young Princes Courage, comes the Death of the Fair Empreſs his Mother; to whom, although he bare all the Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Affection, as became a moſt Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and Loving Child; yet having his Courage heightned by reading the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> be ſubmitted not to Effeminate Tears, but vented his Sorrows in an ingenious Song, Compoſed by him on that Occaſion; which ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice hath not been unluckily Tranſlated; To this purpoſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <head>SONG.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>THe Glories of our Birth and State</l>
                              <l>Are ſhadows, not ſubſtantial Things;</l>
                              <l>There is no Armour 'gainſt our Fate:</l>
                              <l>Death layes his Icy Hands on Kings:</l>
                              <l>Scepter and Crown, muſt tumble down,</l>
                              <l>And in the Duſt be equal laid,</l>
                              <l>With the poor crooked Scithe &amp; Spade.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51812:6"/>
                              <l>Some Men with Swords may reap the fields,</l>
                              <l>And plant freſh Lawrel where they kill:</l>
                              <l>But their ſtrong Nerves at laſt muſt yield;</l>
                              <l>They tame but one another ſtill.</l>
                              <l>Early or late, we bend to Fate,</l>
                              <l>And muſt give up our murmering Breath,</l>
                              <l>Whilſt the pale Captive creeps to Death.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>The Garland's withered on your Brow.</l>
                              <l>Then boaſt no more your mighty Deeds;</l>
                              <l>For on Death's purple Altar, now</l>
                              <l>See where the Victor victime Bleeds:</l>
                              <l>All Heads muſt come, to the cold Tomb;</l>
                              <l>Only the Actions of the Juſt</l>
                              <l>Smell Sweet and bloſſom in the Duſt.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51812:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. By Advice of his Parliament, the Emperor Marrieth the Princeſs <hi>Aphrodiſia,</hi> who hearing of <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> became Enamour'd of him; and ſhews him her Affection.</head>
               <p>THe Solemnities of the Empereſs's Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral being over, the <hi>Senate</hi> doubting, if the Excellent <hi>Eraſtus</hi> dyed, the Royal Line might be Extinct for want of Iſſue, prevailed with <hi>Diocleſian</hi> to admit to his Imbraces the Princeſs <hi>Aphrodicia,</hi> of whoſe Beauty and Breeding, Fame had made a loud Report: The good old Emperor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the more ready to entertain a good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion for the fair Ones of that <hi>Sex,</hi> by reaſon of the excellent Virtues of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Queen, the Mother of his Heir appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſoon yielded to their Requeſt: And had his Wedding celebrated with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Royal Diverſions, as Muſick, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and Ringing the Bells, whilſt they ſung to the Tune of—
<q>
                     <l>Four and Twenty Fidlers all on a Row;</l>
                     <l>And there was Fidle, Fidle, and twice Fidle, Feedle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Eraſtus</hi> was none of the Gallants
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51812:7"/> that attended this Nuptial entertainment, either having a greater inclination for his Studies, or elſe loath to put off the Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his Mother: But all diſcourſes were ſo loaded with the Fame of his Youth, Parts, and excellent Acquirements, that it deafned all the other Muſick of the Court; inſomuch, that the new made Bride could not reliſh the Careſſes of her Amorous So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, for the Pain ſhe was in; being ſmitten with the unknown parts, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of the famous <hi>Eraſtus.</hi> So that letting looſe the Reins of her Affections, ſhe was driven by the violence of Paſſion, thus to make known her Affection to her beloved Prince, and Son-in-Law. Having taken into her Apartment, a Slave that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her for her moſt pleaſant Privacies, and tyed him faſt, by the uſual <hi>Oath of Secreſy,</hi> never to divulge her Story to any Male or Female, but her adored <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> ſhe ſent him with a preſent of very rich Linnen, ſome Plain, ſome Lac'd, with Cravats of Venetian Point, &amp; Shirts curiouſly wrought in Flames, expreſſing this Motto, <hi>Thus do I Mourn for you, and Burn.</hi> Herewith ſhe ſent a Looking-Glaſs carved of precious Stonee, with ſuch Art, that it diverſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the paſſion of <hi>Venus</hi> for <hi>Adonis, Dido</hi> for <hi>Eneas,</hi> with many more, whereof
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51812:7"/> 
                  <hi>Romances</hi> are full; there were alſo coſtly Perfumes of great Virtue to move Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and a Sweet-heart of <hi>Pomander,</hi> made by <hi>Punteus,</hi> which having locked up in a right <hi>Indian</hi> Cabinet, covered with Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligreen of Silver wire; ſhe diſpatched her Meſſenger, commanding him to deliver theſe Preſents, as from the Emperor and her ſelf; but by no means to Omit any poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible demonſtrations of the violence of her Affection to the Youthful Prince; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contemplative in the Garden of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement, was encountred with the amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous preſent from the Queen, his unchaſt Mother-in-Law, which by the Page, was with great artifice preſented in both the Emperor's and her name, deſiring <hi>Eraſtus</hi> to return to the Court, and afford his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with a Father, and Mother, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed him more than her very Life: then drawing out the exquiſite Curioſities that were ſent, and opening them one by one, he failed not to expound the great Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Love the Empereſs had for him, if poſſible, more than for the Emperor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But theſe Gayities obtaining nothing on his <hi>Phyloſophical</hi> conſtitution, had been rejected, had it not been for the interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Seven Wiſe Maſters,</hi> who percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the great richneſs of the Preſent, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51812:8"/> fearing the diſpleaſure of the Emperor or Empreſs, if they ſhould be rejected, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with their princely Pupil to admit them, not without commending his Virtue for thus deſpiſing the tempting vanities of the Court. So the Queens Meſſenger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſmiſſed, he reſolved to diſſemble the ſucceſs to his Miſtreſs, and craftily acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her, That <hi>Eraſtus</hi> had received her To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens with infinite Ioy, kiſſing every part, and praying her that his Affection might be accepted, which he would not fail, vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, to expreſs when he came to <hi>Rome.</hi> This wrought ſo on this beguiled Princeſs, that verily believing her deceitful Slave, ſhe Royally rewarded his Negotiation; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing, if he were inſtrumental in accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing her wiſhes, ſhe would at leaſt get him to be Knighted: And though he had no hope of prevailing againſt the impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Virtue of <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> yet the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his own profit made him nouriſh the Empreſs with feigned hopes of ſucceſs; whilſt ſhe burning in the heat of an intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate deſire, retired into her Cloſet, and caſting her ſelf on her Couch, in a Dream, fancied ſhe had her dear Idea in her Arms; ſo that ſpeaking aloud with the extacy, <hi>Ah! My better Life, you are welcome.</hi> At which noiſe, her Ladies coming into the Room,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51812:8"/> and awakening her, ſhe told them, ſhe had dreamt of a Serpent that affrighted her: whereupon they urging, that no credit was due to Dreams, perſwaded Her Majeſty to divert her ſelf at the Play-houſe, until Supper time.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>SVpper being ended, and the Emperor, and his Queen retired to their Lodging; whilſt the ſoft Diadem of ſound Sleep crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Temples, the wretched Queen could not reſt, fearing an enterprize ſo well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51812:9"/> ſhould miſcarry through her neglect; therefore riſing early in the Morning, and pretending to go to her Beads, ſhe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately writ this Letter to her dear I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Aphrodicia <hi>to</hi> Eraſtus.</head>
                     <p>LEt not your fair Eyes be diſpleaſed with the Rudeneſs of theſe Unpolliſhed, which proceeding from the deepeſt Affection, come to ſhew the unſufferable Pain I endure, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I enjoy the moſt Amiable <hi>Eraſtus.</hi> It is impoſſible a perſon of your Youth and Beauty can be inſenſible of <hi>Cupids</hi> Flame, which ſo preys upon my Vitals, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it be quenched by a reciprocal Ardour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> on your Part, my gaſping Spirits muſt ſoon Expire. In confirmation of my real Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I have herewith ſent the beſt of my Jewels, too mean a preſent for the Maſter of my Heart. The grandure of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire is too mean an Object for her, whoſe Soul cheriſheth your Idea. Come then, and let your Embraces make me happy, or I ſhall ſoon dye the moſt unfortunate of Women.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Letter being ſealed, ſhe placed, with many Iewels of richeſt value, in a Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, whereon, in moſt curious Work, ſhe had taught her Needle to expreſs the Story of <hi>Penelope</hi> and <hi>Uliſſes;</hi> and delivering it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51812:9"/> to her private Meſſenger, ſhe gave him Charge, with all running inſinuations, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xpreſs to the Prince the fervent Ardour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f her Paſſion; which he had the fitter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pportunity to do, finding the Prince alone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his Cloſet: But before he brake into mention of the moſt important matter, be reſolved to ſee with what Countenance the noble <hi>Eraſtus</hi> would receive the Amorous Preſent; but as ſoon as the Letter had diſcovered the true meaning of the Deſign; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow did a virtuous diſdain ſhew it ſelf in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Countenance; and having torn the lewd Epiſtle, with ſharp reproofs he diſmiſſed the Slave, commanding him to adviſe his Miſtreſs to deſiſt her unchaſt and wicked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and to carry back the Tokens of her foul deſire. The Slave, being retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, had no eaſy part to act, being for his own advantage to diſſemble the juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> therefore, craftily, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he acquaints the Queen (who wondered at the return of her Iewels without any Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) That the Prince had returned them, as not eſteeming himſelf worthy of ſo great Rarities, that were fitter for a Ladies Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet; that her Affection, was that which, above all things he valued; and kiſſing the Letter a thouſand times, had returned an anſwer in writing, but ſeared a diſcovery
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51812:10"/> by the ſuddain approach of ſome one of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tutors, only pray'd her, that he might li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in her favour until he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould be ſpeedily; and that then ſhe ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> receive the Satisfaction ſhe ſo much deſire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> This Story infinitely ſatisfied <hi>Aphrodici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> who liberally rewarding her (as ſhe though truſty Slave; with moſt ardent Expectati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe waited the coming of <hi>Eraſtus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>IN the mean time the impatient Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs took all Occaſions, by ſetting b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the Emperor, the great Renown th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would redound to him by the preſence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Son, who was a perſon of ſo rare a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compliſhments, as was not again to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> matched in the World; and that it wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mightily engage the Affections of his Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to ſee before their Eyes a Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch excellent perfections, ſo qualified f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the imperial Diadem. With ſuch Inſinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions ſhe ſoon prevailed on the eaſy <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſian,</hi> who had likewiſe no leſs inclin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion to ſee an only Son of ſuch admirab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Improvement: who ſuddenly diſpatch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one of his principal Lords to the Palace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the young Prince; where having to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51812:10"/> 
                  <hi>Seven Wiſe Maſters</hi> given an account of the Emperors pleaſure, That his Son ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome to <hi>Rome</hi> on the next day, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid <hi>Tutors</hi> accompany him, if they thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> might be without prejudice to the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies of their Royal Pupil. The Learned Maſters having, with much attention, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idered the Emperors meſſage, and knowing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir charge, <hi>Eraſtus</hi> to be accompliſhed to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igheſt degree that Philoſophy could im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove him to. After they had conducted the Ambaſſador to the preſence of the hopeful Son of the Empire, where they propounded ſeveral abſtruce Queſtions in the deepeſt Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Lord might be able to give the Emperor an account of his Sons proficience; which all being anſwered by <hi>Eraſtus</hi> with incomparable Skill, and promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Wit far beyond his years: The Ambaſſador returned the moſt ſatisfied Man alive, acquainting Him, That the next day the young Prince would not fail to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy his Obedience to his Royal pleaſure; and would come attended with his learned Maſters, who all preſented their moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Duty to their Lord the Emperor; which anſwer being received by <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an account of his Sons wonderful proficiency in Learning, it rendered him the moſt joyful Man in the World. So that,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51812:11"/> forthwith he ordered his Senate and Nobles to be ready the next day to mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their young Prince, and with greateſt pom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conduct him to the Court. The whole City was employed in fitting Pageants, Arches<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Equipages for his reception: But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, <hi>Aphrodicia</hi> could hardly ſuppreſs the exceſs of Ioy ſhe was in, at the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſo near approach of that welcom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day, wherein ſhe ſhould enjoy (as ſhe thought) the Object of her moſt fervent Wiſhes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> elevated Deſires: The reſt of the Ladie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> omitted no bravery that might expreſs thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> acknowledgement of the moſt accompliſhed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and deſirable of Mankind.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51812:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>BVt on the Evening before this great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, the young Prince walking in his Garden, obſerved by a croſs aſpect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Stars, that ſome moſt eminent danger threatned him in this his ſplendid expedition; but that which moſt troubled him, was the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an ignominious Death, which by his great skill in Aſtrology he ſaw muſt happen; not ſo much dreading Death, which his Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy taught him was the reſult of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as the ſhameful manner of it: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore communicating this diſcovery to his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Tutors, they heard him with great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, and finding by the Scheams (which on that Occaſion) they erected, that it was but too true, as the Prince had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; they were caſt into the greateſt Sorrow and Deſtraction imaginable; not finding any poſſibility to prevent this ſpeedy Ruin and Deſtruction, in which they muſt all be involved. But Eraſtus, who was ever in an extraordinary manner befriended by the Gods; had it revealed to him, that if he could but keep ſilence for ſeven days, the fatal Aſpect would be over, and he ſhould, with great honour, eſcape the threatened Miſchief: They being convinced of the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of this project, and confirmed in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51812:12"/> belief of it by an Eclips that had hapened not long before: reſolved, being Seven in number, each Man would take his day to Mediate and Intercede for this Innocent Prince, during the time of his Silence, thereby to divert that miſunderſtanding and miſchief, which the Malice of <hi>Eraſtus's</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies might ſuggeſt on that occaſion; which being on all hands reſolved on, they, with moſt Princely Equipage, adreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their Iourney the next Morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>THe morning of this ſplendid day being come, a ſelect company of the Eldeſt Sons of the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobility waited the young Prince's Motion out of the Gate o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Palace, where they attended him, dreſt in the richeſt Habits, moſt deviceful Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitures, and coſtly Liveries, that the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire (then in its Glory) could furniſh them withal: in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Equipage waiting upon him to the City-gate, they were there met by the Empero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in a Chariot of State, and all the Noble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Court; ſome on Horſe-back, other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Coaches curiouſly Guilded, and ſet of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51812:12"/> with the beſt <hi>Italian</hi> Painting, whilſt all the Bells in the City were rung in muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Changes, and the Conduits running with Wine, and the Mayor, and his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries linning the Streets with their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and Liveries; beſides the Pageants, and Rope-dancers, with other pompes of Diverſion, far exceeded the gayity of a Bartholomew-Fair. But all this Triumph was ſoon turned into the greateſt Dejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Sorrow imaginable: when the Emperor ſpeaking to the Son of his beſt hopes, &amp; giving him the welcom of a moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Father, received no other anſwer but a dumb Obeiſance, and ſilent Reverence; at which, the Emperor being in great heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, feared leſt his too much Study might have deprived him of his Reaſon, or that in a too ſtrict purſuit of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> he had loſt his Morrals: this opinion was much hightened, when the young Prince, being conducted into the Chamber of Preſence, and ſate on a Throne by his Father, could by no arguments be prevailed with to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock the Cabinet of his Coral-Lips, but had there Immured the moſt Learned of Tongues to a rigorous Silence: So that calling for the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> the inraged Emperor with great tranſport and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence, told them, That if they did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51812:13"/> reſtore his Son to his Speech, both they and their ſottiſh Pupil ſhould ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect to be condemned to the Houſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Silence, and have the Organs of their Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſtopped by Ax of Iuſtice: But they, with the greateſt Submiſſions that could he endeavoured to allay the mighty Tempeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Kings wrath, aſſuring His Majeſty. That this wonderful ſilence of his Son, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it did proceed from ſome ſecret cauſe, to them unknown, ſo they doubted not bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time would manifeſt, that it was by ſome divine power, or command at leaſt, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the wiſeſt of Princes had impoſed this ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence on himſelf: For that the Lord tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had brought the Emperors Meſſage, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the day before, was witneſs with what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent demonſtration of Reaſon and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he had diſcourſed in his preſence bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the day before.</p>
               <p>But the Queen, who ſitting under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cloath of State in the ſame Room, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been all this while devouring with her Eyes the dear Object of her higheſt deſires; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> finding that flame, which report had kindled was now ſo much heightened by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the moſt attractive, and deſirabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſon in the World, that without it were a little allayed by a ſpeedy fruition, it would certainly reduce her to be the moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51812:13"/> of Women; took this occaſion to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the indulgent Emperor, that ſhe had in her Cloſet a Secret, recommended by a Phyſitian of great note, that would in ſhort time recover the ſpeech of ſuch as were dumb: Therefore if His Majeſty would ſo order it, that the Prince might retire with her, to her Apartment, ſhe doubted not but in ſome ſhort time, if ſhe had him alone with her, both to diſcover, and cure the cauſe of his Diſtemper.</p>
               <p>The good Emperor, not ſuſpecting this Serpentine cunning of a fair Woman, gave command, That <hi>Eraſtus</hi> ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon the Queen in her Cloſet; where this worſt of Women put in practice, the devillish deſign you will hear of in the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>THe Luſtful <hi>Aphrodiſia</hi> having by this occaſion, as ſhe thought, taken ſure hold of her Prey: the doors being ſhut, ſhe, with moſt amorous words and geſtures, began to explain the meaning of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Letters and preſents, recounting the violence of her paſſion, in the moſt intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51812:14"/> manner that a wicked and depraved Woman can deviſe. And is my Beauty <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> and my Youth, that is here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to your pleaſure, become an object of ſcorn and contempt: Am I the occaſion of this ſtupid ſilence of yours? ſpeak my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> and e're it be too late, revive the languiſhing Spirits of her that cannot live without ſhe enjoyes you. Then with a ſtorm of lacivious Kiſſes, ſhe attempted a battery on the impregnable Fort of his Chaſtity; expoſing her moſt enticeing beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with the greateſt alurement; and hightening the demonſtrations of her paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by words, expreſſing the moſt arden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſincere Affection: What <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> my <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> muſt then my royal Favour, and all conquering Beauty be the contempt of your pretended ſtupidity, and icy ſilence or can you think, though you abuſe theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tears, the ſhowers of my Love, that you ſhall be able to avoid the tempeſt of my juſt Anger? No, no, <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> think no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy dull Morallity ſhall balk my expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their deſired end; but that tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mayſt ſee how far the mallice of a diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Woman can reach, be aſſured I will make ſo effectual an example of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male rage, as ſhall aſtoniſh the Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to come, when they ſhall here there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51812:14"/> Then trying whither force might not prevail upon him, ſhe endeavoured to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain him to her Couch; which the poor tranſported Prince perceiving, with great nimbleneſs, ſeized the door, left the infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Room; but was ſoon purſued through the Gallery by the enraged Empreſs, whoſe Luſt being now turned to helliſh and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Revenge, ſhe was heard over the Court, with moſt feigned, and <hi>Crocadile</hi> Lamentations, to exclaim, ſtop, ſtop, the young Traitor to his Fathers honour, the Viola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or of my Chaſticy, with many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Blaſphemies, as her deviliſh and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Malice could invent; ſtill tearing her Hair, rendring her Face and Breaſts, and ſhattering her neglected Iewels, and regal Robes, that ſhould have been the modeſt covering of her Honour: So that meeting the King in this poſture, who had by this time detained the innocent Prince, whom he met flying the beaſtial Rage of this Fury: caſting her ſelf at his Royal Feet, ſhe, with great artifice ſo acted the Hypocrite, that the Emperor was gull'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a belief of that ſhameleſs Fact, which this moſt Savage of her Sex had alleadged, with feigned tears, and bitter execrations. So that taking the Princes ſilence (which the Stars had joyned him) for a contempt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51812:15"/> of his Authority, and an infallible argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Guilt; he ordered the Guards to to take this model of abuſed Innocence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to cloſe Cuſtody, until it ſhould be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined what Sentence was the juſt reward of ſo foul a Crime.</p>
               <p>Which was ſoon reſolved on, for the Council being preſently called, and having only heard the Plaintif (who now undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded ſhe had a plenary revenge on the Contemner of her brutal deſires) they Sentenced him to be draw'd, hanged, and guarter'd; and that within the ſpace of three hours: But all were aſtoniſhed that beheld his unmoved Conſtancy under this moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt proceedure; and greatly Lamented, that a young Prince, of ſuch growing hopes, ſhould be thus cut off in the bud, and morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Princely youth: So that nothing but diſmal Lamentations were to be heard, and ſable Conſternation appeared to cover the Face of the whole City. This gave ſo great an Alaram to the <hi>Seven Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> who had engaged to be his Advocates for the ſeven dayes, until the Malignity of his Stars were expired; that they hardly knew what to determine, becauſe of the ſhortneſs of the time: But withal conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, if they moved not in this inſtant, the Fortune of the Empire would be loſt,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51812:15"/> and Poſterity deprived of the happineſs of ſo excellent a Governour. The Lot for the firſt day fell on <hi>Euproſigorus;</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly addreſſed himſelf to oppoſe the Torrent of the imperial Rage, in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that direful Sentence on the beſt of Princes, <hi>Eraſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>NO ſooner had <hi>Euproſigorus</hi> entered the preſence of <hi>Diocleſian;</hi> but it may well be imagined what a ſtorm of fury fell on him for his preſumption, in that he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51812:16"/> had intruded himſelf upon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors preſence, when his fury, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport on the forementioned occaſion were ſuch, as none durſt attempt to come into his ſight: Eſpecially ſuch as he thought the Tutors to the unfortunate <hi>Eraſtus</hi> muſt be, having inſtead of the excellent dictates of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> (as he thought) inſtructed him in nothing more than to ſeek the ſhame and ruine of himſelf, and caſt perpetual infamy on his Parents. I ſay 'tis not hard to gueſs how welcome <hi>Euproſigorus</hi> muſt needs be to a preſence that had entertained ſuch thoughts as theſe confirming him. But the good <hi>Philoſopher</hi> arming himſelf with the Male of innocence, and the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Care the Gods had over ſuch, without the leaſt ſhew of trouble or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, thus replied to the Emperor; having given place to the firſt ſhocks of his fury. And is it then (moſt excellent <hi>Diocleſian</hi>) ſo ſmall a thing (ſaid he) with one ſuddain, and undeliberate ſtroke to cut of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your ſtock, I had almoſt ſaid of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, through the importunities; nay, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps falſe ſuggeſtions of a weak and ſilly woman, whoſe Paſſions ſometimes admit not of the Councels of reaſon or delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Hear me then mighty Emperor (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he) and ſuſpend this rigid Sentence
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51812:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> until I have (by commemorating an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that once befell in this City) ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Highneſs the irrecoverable loſs that attends a haſty and raſh Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which requeſt being complied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; he aſſumes his diſcourſe to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. There was not many years ſince, a noble Man of this your Emperial City, who had one only Child, which he delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the care of a Nurſe, to be brought up in his own Houſe; he had beſides a Dog, in which he took great ſatisfaction; for many qualities incident to that active and faithful Creature, in the which he had obſerved this Dog to excel. Now it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened on a certain day, when this Lord, with his Lady and Attendants, went to ſee a Tournament performed in the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpick</hi> fields, according to the cuſtome of the antient <hi>Romans;</hi> and having left only the Nurſe with the care of their darling Child, her curioſity carried her to the top of the houſe, to obſerve what ſhe could of the Sport at ſo great a diſtance, leaving only the fond Dog in the Room, where the Child ſlept in its Cradle; but whilſt this careleſs Woman was there diverting her iule and wanton Fancy, a Serpent came into the Chamber where the Infant lay, which ſoon eſpied by the truſty Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51812:17"/> was as ſoon ſet upon, in defence of the dear little Pledge, whoſe charge he maintained; the Conteſt was fierce and long, ſo that in the fray, the Cradle was overthrown, but to ſuch advantage, that it ſecured the Child from what it might otherwiſe have been expoſed to: At length the Dog won the Victory; but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the loſs of much Blood; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perceived by the careleſs Nurſe, as ſoon as her impertinence gave her leave to deſcend into the Chamber; without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enquiry, ſhe flies, with the Alarum, to the Place where her Lady was, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing the faithful Spanniel that had been the protector of his little Maſter, to have been his Deſtroyer. All enter the Room with all that haſt which Paſſion and Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry could convey them withall, and finding the Cradle overthrown, the honeſt Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian bloody; without more ado, rewarded his Fidelity by knocking out his Brains, thereby robbing the pooor Dog of his life, that had been the Inſtrument to preſerve the Childs. But when a little reſpite and breathing had given them leave to ſearch for the deplored Infant; it was found alive, and entire, under the Cradle; and on a ſtricter view, the remains of a venomous Serpent, from whom the truſty
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51812:17"/> Dog had received his wounds in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters defence: when theſe and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances began more clamly to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lected upon; then indeed did the errours of raſh &amp; precipitate paſſion ſhew themſelves in their true colours: Inſomuch, that the too credulous Gentleman now ſaw, how, for want of conſideration, he had rewarded the valiant and faithful Defender of his Child and Houſe, with a baſe, cruel, and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Death; and believing it impoſſible, that ever ſuch another faithful Servant could fall to the ſhare of one that knew no better to diſtinguiſh his ſervices: theſe, and ſuch like reflections had like to have put him on the ſending Wife, Nurſe, and Servants into the other World, to expiate the irreparable loſs of his truſty Spanniel. This, mighty Sir, may be your caſe, and much worſe, if by the advice of your wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Councellors, you do not take ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in this great and important Affair, as the juſt merit of the Cauſe requires. Wherefore let me crave your Royal defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of this ſo raſh and ſevere Sentence; which the Emperor (being much taken with the Morality of the Story) granted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51812:18"/>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>IN the Evening going to the Apartment of the Empreſs, as he was want to do; having the greateſt tenderneſs of Affection for her, by reaſon of the great attraction youth naturally over Age: he found her all in tears, and with bitter ſobs venting (it may be) one of the dolefulleſt Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that e're was heard of: But that which moſt aſtonished the good <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> was to obſerve, that the more he endeavoured
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51812:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> to adminiſter to the mittigation of her Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows; the more they were exaſperated, and broke out with no ſmall reflections on his being wholly a ſtranger to all principles of Iuſtice, and common Honeſty; for (ſaid she) as the place you hold in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire obligeth you to the ſtricteſt obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Laws of Iuſtice and Equity; So the perſonal Relation you ſtand in to me, more particularly requires at your hand a due vindication of my Honour, but both of theſe you have much departed from, in delaying the reparation of the violence offered to your Bed, as well as mine, by him whom you call your Son; but what proportion his actions bear to that Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let the world judge. In this caſe I can compare you no better to any thing, than the old <hi>Pine</hi> Tree: What <hi>Pine</hi> Tree, ſaid the Emperor? She replied, becauſe the caſe is ſo parallel, I will give you the trouble to hear it; and compoſing her Face to a formal ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riouſneſs, she began thus, A Gentleman that took great delight in an Vmbrage he had near his Garden, and eſpecially to an old <hi>Pine</hi> Tree that gave great Ornament to it: One day as he was contemplating in the shade of that place, he obſerved a young ſprout ariſe from the root of the ancient <hi>Pine,</hi> and taking his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51812:19"/> Gardiner, conſulted how to preſerve and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the young Tree. The Gardiner told him, that the bigger Pine bore too much head, which ſhaded and hindered; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he had order to pare that part of the old Pine that was injurious to the Sprout: The Gentleman about that time took a jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and at his return, found one half of the old Tree withered; and asking again his Gardiner, had this anſwer, That it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wholly to take away the ancient Pine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the young might the ſooner fill his place. This my Lord, this is what I fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I wiſh my Omens prove not too true; as for inſtance, Your Majeſty is the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pine, under whoſe ſhaddow the Roman Shepheards have with non-interrupted de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light repoſed themſelves: your ſuppoſed Son is the fatal ſhrub, for whoſe cheriſhment, your Royal Self, the Emperial Pine, muſt be cut down &amp; deſtroyed; they having killed your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part, your Honor already: The Gardiners are theſe baſe Sycophants; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philoſophers, who (ſo they may divide the Government of Rome between them) are all bent to the cheriſhing this graceleſs Shrub. And here a well-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled Tide of Tears ſtopt the farther current of her ſpeech; ſo that looking moſt diſconſolately on the Emperor, as expecting his anſwer to her diabollical Fable: ſhe might ſee him make ſeveral demonſtrations of his too abſolute belief of her ſham, by thumping his breaſt, beating the ground, curſing the very gods, &amp; endeavouring to dart
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51812:19"/> his fury at them, in the fierce caſt of his eyes and countenance: At length, Too well my dear Empreſs (ſaid he) do I diſcern this execrable Conſpiracy; but I hope it ſhall not be too late: then leaving the room, he immediately gave the ſecond order for exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the dire Sentence on the Peerleſs Eraſtus.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>THe Philoſopher Dimurgus have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to take off the ſecond days ſhock from the innocent Eraſtus; in order to the ſeaſonable effecting it, very early in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51812:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> morning was waiting at the door of the Kings Chamber, and being introduced by one of the Pages, had the liberty of being heard, with greater patience than one could have thought was poſſible, conſidering the dreadful ferment the laſt diſcourſe, with <hi>Aphrodicea,</hi> had put the Emperor in: but whether it was that the ſlumbers of the Night had ſomewhat moderated the acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Fumes; or only adviſeing his Pillow, abſtracted ſomewhat from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of his reſolution. <hi>Certes</hi> (as we were ſaying) <hi>Dimurgus</hi> found him in a temper much more ſerene, than could have been expected: the circumſtances, but now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, being conſidered, which gave the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> more freedom to debate the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Sentence, than otherwiſe could have been permitted; inſomuch, that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a ſecond days Truce, with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors indignation: which he did, by rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſad, and moſt unfortunate adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the learned <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> in this ſort.</p>
               <p>The young Prince of <hi>Hungary</hi> being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſick, the King and Queen ſent Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors to the famous Doctor, with large preſents, and aſſurance of larger, if he would come and ſecure the life of their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son: It ſo happened at that time, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51812:20"/> old Phyſitian had himſelf need of a Doctor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Meſſengers ſeeing him not in capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to Travel, accepted of a young Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, a Nephew of <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> whom he had, with all diligence, inſtructed in the greateſt Secrets of his Art: this perſon being arrived at the Court, was very well received by both the King and Queen, who diſcovered in him, more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſymptoms of an exquiſite Artiſt.</p>
               <p>One day taking the Queen aſide, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately he acquainted her, That the young Prince, now ſo ſick, was not the natural Son of the King; and therefore, unleſs ſhe would relate who was his real Father, he could do no more towards his Cure; but on conſideration ſhe would diſcloſe that, he would ſecure the young Princes life. The Queen much aſtoniſhed at his great Art; after having taken of him an Oath of Secreſy on the Maſs-book, and modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquainted him with the Circumſtances inducing her thereto; which, without Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, you may ſuppoſe to be the King's coldneſs, and a natural Inclination that Queens have to furniſh the world with Princes, that have the Spirit of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: She acquaintes him with the only Secret of her Cabinet, that he was the Son of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man, that had ſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51812:21"/> King in his Wars againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> who taking the opportunity of the King's being gone a Hunting; one day took ſuch acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with me in my Cloſet, that after ſome time, it was the product of this Son; who indeed paſſeth for the Prince: and I promiſed the Captain, for his kindneſs to me, to make his child (if a boy) Heir to the Crown of <hi>Hungary.</hi> By this the King hath the ſatisfaction to think himſelf a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; I the happineſs of being a Mother: and you the only perſon entruſted with the Secret, of the which, you may make ſuch uſe as beſt pleaſeth you, only preſerving the Sons life, and the Mothers Honour; which I am the eaſier induced to confide in, by reaſon of your Oath to <hi>Hipocrates.</hi> The young Doctor having given great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to this Relation; promiſed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer both her requeſts, both in relation to the Secret, and to apply himſelf to uſe his utmoſt skill for the recovery of the young Prince; which he did with ſuch ſucceſs, that in a little time he being perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, to the exceeding ſatisfaction both of the King and Queen: the Phyſitian was Royally rewarded, and diſmiſſed with great Honour; who returning to his Unkle, the great <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> and having given him a particular account of his good Succeſs,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51812:21"/> with the extraordinary bounty of his Royal Benefactors. The ſubtle old Doctor ſeem'd wonderfully pleaſed with what his Nephew had related; and forced himſelf into an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of highly congratulating the young Mans fortune; whilſt inwardly he had ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry different reſentments: for it wrought in him a ſtrong regret, which at length ſwell up to a perfect maligning, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining at the proſperity of this young Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; and as it is natural for old men to be largely ſtockt with jealouſy, and envy: Theſe two paſſions wrought ſo powerfully on the declining <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> that he put on a felonious reſolution of eclipſing the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grandure of his kinſman, leſt in time it might exceed the dimenſion of his own long acquired Fame. He therefore takes his kinſman into the fields, one day, to obſerve the mediciaal Herbs of the earth, and having asked him divers queſtions of the nature and quality of ſuch and ſuch Plants; at length, ſaid the old Man, reach me that Herb that groweth ſo low on the ground; which the young Doctor ſtooping to do, the other mortally wounded him on the hinder part of his head, with a hatchet he (for that purpoſe) had placed under his Gown. Thus this envious old man having put a period to his life; and as (he the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:51812:22"/> thought) to his own fears and jealouſies, he caſt the Body in a pit thereby, inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoycing at the bloody Tragedy. But a very ſhort time convinced him of the barbarous effect of his raſh and indeliberate Action, when being ſeized with a violent diſtemper; the pains, and decay's of his Body put him in mind of his cruel Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; beſides, wanting now the help of his only Nephew, whom ſo baſely he had but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chered. So that continually exclaiming on the irrecoverable loſs his raſhneſs had brought on all Men, and particularly on himſelf, and filled with the Terrours of black horror, and endleſs deſpair, he moſt wretchedly expired in one of his Agonies. Thus (mighty Prince) ſaid the learned <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murgus,</hi> have I laid before your Emperial Majeſty, the moſt ſad, and irreparable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of raſh, and inconſiderate Actions; which once finiſhed, and determined, can never be repaired; but end in endleſs, yet vain Repentance. The Emperor having weighed the purport of this diſcourſe, orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a ſecond Reprieve to the diſmal Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:51812:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>THe ungracious Empreſs ſéeing the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Dimurgus,</hi> had prevailed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpit the fatal Sentence againſt the moſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> and fearing the delay of his Execution, might one day diſcover her inhuman Treachery, and pull a juſt venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on her own head: that ſhe might yet again incence the blinded Emperor to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with her barbarous Treaſons; feigned her ſelf almoſt dead with ſorrow, becauſe her Honour had not received that ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Law had granted to the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her Complaint. Wherefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tireing into the moſt private part of her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, ſhe permitted none to adminiſter Comfort to her Sorrows, but the Slave that had been the Secretary to her devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh practices. This ſad retirement coming to the Emperors ears; he out of an exceſs of Affection, would go to comfort his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable <hi>Crocadile,</hi> and being, with great entreaties, admitted to the place, which was the doleful Scene of her feigned Sorrow; he found her weltering in tears, in the midſt of her Roſaries and Beads, afflicting her ſelf in the moſt paſſionate manner imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51812:23"/> ſo that the poor deluded <hi>Diocleſian</hi> could not forbear ſhedding his Royal Iuice at the diſmal proſpect. Till having almoſt tired her ſelf with the exceſs of her fiction, and (as ſhe thought) mollified him to take the impreſſion of her curſed Council: She thus adres'd her ſelf to her deſign. Think you, moſt Royal <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> that theſe tears, and this profound ſorrow in which you ſee me caſt, could poſſibly proceed on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the moſt unfortunate <hi>Aphrodicea?</hi> or that my own affairs (which bear no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in my Soul with yours) could work me to ſo ſharp regret? No, mighty Prince, it is the eminent danger that I ſee your Sacred Perſon expoſed to, whilſt you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe ungracious, and traiterous <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi> to work you into a belief of <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi>'s innocence: That <hi>Eraſtus</hi> (ſaid ſhe) whom I cannot mention without an Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and here ſtopping her ſpeech, which gave way to a volly of Sighs, and well-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled Groans; and fixing her <hi>Baſilisk</hi> eyes on the almoſt diſtracted Emperor, ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded after this ſort: The Gods, and all the Supream Powers ever defend the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, and never ſuffer my ominous portents to take effect on his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Perſon. Oh! my Soveraign <hi>Diocleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> (ſaid ſhe) How like are you to the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51812:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> Bore, of which the <hi>Moraliſt</hi> gives ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count? who having long ſwayed the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Foreſt, and with great contempt overthrown the pride, and power of all that oppoſed his Empire; yet at laſt was by a wilely ſtratagem, and ſeeming friendſhip de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, by a ſtily Sheapherd, after this manner: This treacherous Swain had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a ſtately Pear-tree, the Fruit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, beſt pleaſed the princely Bore, and to the which, for that reaſon he made frequent reſort: The Heardſman takes an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to convey himſelf upon this Tree; where having been but little time, the generous Bore came to his repaſt, and giving the Tree a ſhog, to ſhake down his delicates, the cunning Swain had gathered many in his coat, which at that inſtant he flung down to the Royal Beaſt, and ever now and then ſent freſh ſupplies of the delicious fruit, until at length (having made too large a meal) the unwary Bore lay down to reſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fatal Tree: the traiterous youth ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hold of this opportunity, ſoftly deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and gently clawing the ſlumbering Prince, ſoon had an opportunity to thruſt his knife to his heart: To whom the expireing Bore thus ſpake; Perſidious wretch, who in contempt of my Royal Authority, haſt thus traiterouſly deſtroyed my perſon; know, that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51812:24"/> if I had known what poiſonous fruit had been on this ingrateful Tree, I would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave ſet fire to the roots of it: and have by the ruine of ſuch a deceitful Caitif, have prevented my own. What need any Explanation to be made of a parallel ſo viſible? But if your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Highneſs take not warning by this Story, you may too ſoon feel the Sword of him that now claws and flatters you, ſheath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your Bowels. This Advice, ſet off with the greateſt Artifice that a ſubtle malice could deviſe, wrought with the eaſy King, that he once more promiſed the falſe <hi>Aphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea,</hi> that the next riſing Sun ſhould be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Tragedy of <hi>Eraſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:51812:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>THe third dayes care of the excellent Prince <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> by Lot, falling on the wiſe <hi>Philoſopher Thermus;</hi> and he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the ſtrict order the Emperor had given for the punctual Execution of the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sentence, that day, very early in the morning waited at the Royal Apartment: And though he conſidered he was to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the anger of an Emperor, exaſperated by the wiles, and ſubtilties of an implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wicked Queen; yet did the ſence he had of the Iuſtice of the Princes cauſe, the Innocence of his perſon; together with the indiſpenſible duty of a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> to withſtand (what in him lay) the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Sentence ſo barbarous, and againſt the very light of Nature: theſe, and ſuch like conſiderations, armed the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> againſt the mighty oppoſition he met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; ſo that notwithſtanding he was (with much difficulty) admitted to the preſence, and with many a Regal frown, and ſharp reflection entertained by <hi>Diocleſian:</hi> he with great humanity, and undiſturbedneſs, gave way to the paſſionate Tempeſt; and with a Stoical bravery overcame, or at leaſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51812:25"/> deſpiſed the effects of an Emperors blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a Queens rage. So that taking a convenient opportunity, he with a ſage and graceful preſence, and diſcourſe, ſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> charmed the evil ſpirit, that the Magick o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Aphrodicea</hi> had raiſed in the Emperor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that the half-ſubdued <hi>Diocleſian</hi> gave way to the Morals of the learned <hi>Thermus;</hi> which, in ſuch ſort, be expreſſed: That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiſe man (by over-indulging, either his own Paſſions, or the Councils of a ſecret Enemy) may be induced to an Act of the higheſt raſhneſs, and injuſtice: and that a remedileſs, and irreparable miſchief, may be the product of ſuch undeliberate deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, hath been proved by the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diſcourſes of the Sages, <hi>Euproſigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and <hi>Dimurgus.</hi> Now (by the permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your Imperial Majeſty) I humbly crave leave to Infer, that all this miſchief may probably derive from the malice, and ſubtlety of a miſchevious Woman: And though we ought alwayes to be cautious, and ſuſpitious of our own Determinations; eſpecially in matters of Importance (and what can be of greater, than the Fate of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, which depends on the execution, or remiſſion of this dayes Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence) yet ought we never to be more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in ſuch-Affairs, than when a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51812:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall be the Inſtigatreſs of the Action: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> having been alwayes obſerveable, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he moſt notorious, and deſperate Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies have been managed, either by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il, or aſiſtance of that Sex. So having obtained a Reprieval of the Sentence till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he next day, he went on with his Story, as the Author hath it. A Wealthy (but Antient) Noble-man of <hi>Toſcany,</hi> was Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied to a young and beautiful Lady, of one of the moſt Honourable houſes of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry, to the great ſatisfaction of all their Relations; this Marriage was celebrated with all ſuitable demonſtrations of Mirth and Gallantry: So that Feaſting, Dance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Maſqueing, and Entertainment, took up almoſt as much time, as might well have lookt towards a Goſiping; when all this while the old Knight dreſſing himſelf in a Habit, and Humour more agreeable to a Lad of Eighteen, and being in his own Imagination, at leaſt Thirty years younger than his true date: by the brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his behaviour, ſeemed (tollerably) to anſwer the gayity of his young Lady. But theſe Dancing dayes being over, and the old Knight appearing in bed to be quite another thing than what his dreſs, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces humor beſpake him, occaſioned the young Bride to paſs the Night in conſiderations
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51812:26"/> very different from what they might hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been, had ſhe been Married to one, mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuitable to her years: For the old man ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only tickled her into a longing, for tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which was not in his power to give; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that being almoſt diſtracted, with a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire of enjoying a more agreeabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bed-fellow; and having wearied her thought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with caſting, how to accompliſh it: ſhe on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day took an occaſion to diſcloſe her (as ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> call'd it) unſupportable Paſſion to her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and being with her in her Cloſet, ſhe thus beſpake her: Madam, you have now before your eyes, one of the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate of woman kind; Married to what I muſt ever Loath, becauſe he can never afford me the only ſolace of a womans life: think with your ſelf dear Madam, was ever one of my Form and Age, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to be tyed up to a Flaxen-Perri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wig, a Point-band, a trim'd pair of Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taloons, Fringe-Gloves, and a Beaver-Hat; for at night, when the Page hath laid theſe in the dreſſing Room, there remains nothing youthy, nothing handſom, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy my Embraces; when by my ſide lies the ſad Skelleton of a decayed human, which inſtead of giving me the relliſh of my life, grates my thoughts all the long night, with apprehenſions of unwelcome
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51812:26"/> Death. Oh! cruel Matrimony, that fette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt youth under ſuch Tyrannous reſtraints. I therefore humbly implore your Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y affection, as ever you have been ſcorched with the Flame of Love; that you will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe ſome endeavour to eaſe this my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ufferable pain, and afford ſome refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my languiſhing ſpirits. The good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld Lady being ſtrangely ſurprized at this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſcourſe of her Daughters, and dreading <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he conſequence of ſuch unruly Paſſion, diſſembled her true Reſentments, and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to condole with the young woman in her misfortunes; by this means, deſigning to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind out a prevention for the threatning miſchief: She therefore deſired to know whether ſhe had fixed on any Object, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular for the ſatisfying her deſires, and promiſed her beſt aſiſtance therein. The Daughter not perceiving her Mothers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation, took all ſhe ſaid for true, and caſting her ſelf on her knees; Dear Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (ſaid ſhe) you are by this moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate Grant become twice my Mother; for by your aſſiſtance herein, you will ſave that Life, which before you gave me. Then ſhe proceeded to acquaint her, that her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour was (as ſhe thought) one of the moſt Amiable, and Charming perſons in the world: for Madam (continued ſhe) his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51812:27"/> Eyes are ſo piercing, his Diſcourſe ſo ſof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and courtly, his whole Meen ſo attractive that if you can but ſo bring it to paſs, I may have the enjoyment of his perſon; I would not change Fortune with the greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Empreſs. I will repeat you a Song, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the other day, after Confeſſion, he ſung t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my Guittar, which he found in my Cloſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and I am apt to think he utter'd it in com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mileration of my Circumſtances: the Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was this:
<q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="song">
                              <head>SONG.</head>
                              <lg n="1">
                                 <head>I.</head>
                                 <l>NOw fye upon him: What is Man,</l>
                                 <l>Whoſe Life at beſt is but a Span?</l>
                                 <l>When to an Inch it dwindles down;</l>
                                 <l>Ice in his Bones, Snow on his Crown;</l>
                                 <l>That he within his crazy Brain,</l>
                                 <l>Kind thoughts of Love ſhould entertain:</l>
                                 <l>That he, when Harveſt comes ſhould Plow</l>
                                 <l>And when 'tis time to Reap, go Sow;</l>
                                 <l>Who (in Imagination only ſtrong)</l>
                                 <l>Though twice a Child, can never twice b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap> young</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg n="2">
                                 <head>II.</head>
                                 <l>Nature did thoſe ordain for Fools,</l>
                                 <l>That ſue for Work, yet have no Tools:</l>
                                 <l>What fellow-feeling can there be,</l>
                                 <l>In ſuch a ſtrange diſparitie?</l>
                                 <pb n="47" facs="tcp:51812:27"/>
                                 <l>Old Age miſtakes the youthful Breaſt;</l>
                                 <l>For Love dwells there, not Intereſt:</l>
                                 <l>Alas good Man! take thy repoſe,</l>
                                 <l>Get Ribband for thy Thumbs and Toes,</l>
                                 <l>Provide thee Flan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>el, and a ſheet of Lead;</l>
                                 <l>Think on thy Coffin, not thy Bridal Bed.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Song ended, Madam (ſaid he) I hope you will pardon this Levity; and with a look <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat teſtified his compaſſion for my unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he left the Room. Think Deareſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, what impreſſion ſuch a diſcovery, of ſo deſirable an Affection, muſt needs make; and how welcome ſuch a Feaſt muſt be to one acquainted with nothing but broken Meals and Abſtinence: If therefore I have any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in your Motherly Compaſſion! Let me beg your beſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lp in aſſiſting me to the enjoyment of the Chaplains embraces; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, I muſt be the moſt miſerable of Woman kind. The good old Lady was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly much grieved at this diſcovery of her Daughters diſloyalty, and unchaſt inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; yet ſeemingly aſſented, telling her, That ſhe would, with all immaginable ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy and diligence further her deſigns: but that for the greater ſecurity, it were conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to make tryal of the old Man's humor, by croſſing and affronting him in ſome other circumſtance, before they attempted an Abuſe ſo groſs and infamous: So that, if ſhe could but hanſomly acqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> her ſelf, if ſhe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two or three injuries upon him, in ſome
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51812:28"/> other reſpect, firſt of all, it might be a means the better to work his diſpoſition to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with hers in the main deſign, at leaſt it might bring him to yield her a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, that might be uſeful towards the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of her deſires.</p>
               <p>The young Lady (though ſhe thought o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothing more than preſent enjoyment, yet) by the advice of her Mother, aſſented firſt to attempt ſome notable Abuſe, by croſſing him in ſomething or other he was fond of; and this reſolution ſhe ſpeedily put in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice; for ſhe was no ſooner returned to her Parlour, but ſhe preſently knockt a little Beagle Bitch on the head; a Bitch, for which the old Knight had a greater eſteem, than for any Horſe in his Stable; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, when it was firſt diſcovered to him, he only gently Admoniſht her not to deſtroy any thing that he liked without his conſent; and ſoon ſeemed to have forgot it: She therefore, the day following, cut up an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Plumb tree that ſtood in his Garden, the Fruit whereof was very delicate, and fair; and therefore he was very tender of this Tree: This indeed put the Knight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a heat more than was uſual; ſo that, with ſome paſſion, demanding the reaſon of her why ſhe had done it, he was ſoon anſwered, that it ſpoiled the form of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51812:28"/> walks, and that ſhe intended to have a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Flowers in the place of it. The good old Man gave way to the humour of his young Wife in this; whereupon ſhe conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the day was her own, and therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints her Mother with the Succeſs: tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her, That doubtleſs her Husband could not be offended with what ever liberty ſhe took in the ſatisfaction of her Humour: To the which, the prudent Matron made this Reply, Daughter, it is very probable that your Husband (through his great Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to your Youth) may give way to you it matters of ſo ſmall Importance as a Dog, or a Tree, but if you ſhould injure him in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing reflecting on his Honour, you might find him not ſo eaſily Appeaſed; for old Men are never more Iealous, and Implacable, than when toucht upon that Sore. I have therefore thought on an Expedient, how you may try him in that point, and if you therein can Acquit your ſelf with the ſame Succeſs, as in the other two Experiments, I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the next day to accompliſh your Wiſhes. This laſt Promiſe was ſo powerful with the young Lady, that had it been to have leapt out at a Window, ſhe would ſcarce have ſtuck at it, in order to the Conſummating her Wiſhes: ſhe therefore entreats her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to let her know what this laſt Tryal
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51812:29"/> might be, and aſſures her, ſhe will not fail to attempt it. Said then the old Lady, You know divers Friends have an Invitation to Dine with your Husband three days hence, therefore I adviſe you, when we are all juſt ſate at Table, that you pretend to have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got your Knife, and having ſecretly taken hold of the Table-cloath, you haſtily ſtart up to fetch your Knife, and draw all the Plates and Diſhes on the Floor. If therefore you come cleaverly off with this, I will make good my Promiſe. Nothing ſtuck with the young Wife, but that it muſt be three days more before ſhe could hope the Enjoyment of her Wiſhes, which ſhe lookt upon to be three Ages; but at laſt, the day being come, the Gueſts met, the Table richly Furniſhed with variety of the Rarities, according to the Seaſon; the Chaplain having craved a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and all prepared to partake of the ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Treat: on a ſuddain, down come the coſtly Diſhes, with their Garniſhes and Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, on the Ground. This ſtrange Accident was no ſmall ſuprizal to the Knight, as well as his noble Gueſts: But by reaſon of their preſence, he ſeemed to take no notice of it, farther than to put it off with a Laugh, and making it a part of their Mirth to diſcourſe of it: in the mean time the Servants had ſoon covered the Table with another brigad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:51812:29"/> of Diſhes, not inferior to the former; ſo that the Entertainment of the day was not at all leſſened thereby. Muſick, Dancing, and Cards, took up a great part of the night: when every one ſatisfied with the Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of their Entertainment, took their Leaves, leaving the old Knight to conſider a way how to cure his Wifes Levity, and ſhe how the next day to entertain her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor. But the Morning of this much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Day being come, the Knight ſent one of his Pages for his Chirurgeon, who, with many menaces and threats, was forced to draw ſo much Blood from the Armes of the young Lady, as for that time ſtopped the Calenture of her Luſt. The fainting Daughter ſent for her Indulgent Mother; who glad at heart, that her deſign had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the wiſht Succeſs; and that her Daughter was thereby prevented of ſtaining the Honour of her Family by her wanton Embraces; gave her the ſober Advice, for time to come, to mind her Duty to her Lord and Husband, and not to think of a Lacivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous violating that Bed, which ſhe was bound to Preſerve from all Pollution. The Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing young Lady ſhewing great Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, promiſed ſo to do, to the great ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of all her Friends.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:51812:30"/>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Philoſopher Thermus</hi> having ended his elegant Narrative, much to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the Emperor; needed not make any Comment thereon; for every Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance had made deep Impreſſion on the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible part of <hi>Diocleſian:</hi> So that diſmiſſing the Wiſe Man, with Royal Thanks for his ſeaſonable Admonition; the good <hi>Diocleſian</hi> had put on a Reſolution of having the Caſe of his Son, the excellent <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> debated in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51812:30"/> full Senate: but had that determination fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by the moſt miſchevious of her Sex, the Implacable <hi>Aphrodicea;</hi> who finding her Wiles not likely to take; but that by the Wiſdom of the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> they had been hitherto prevented, and fearing that if <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> were permitted to Live, it would at ſome time or other diſcover her deviliſh Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures: She therefore, in the greateſt rage of one in Deſparation, threatned to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge upon her own perſon, the loſs of her Honour, and diſappointment of her barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous deſign on the Innocent young Prince. So retireing to her Chamber, and ſhutting all her Servants out of her Preſence, ſhe gave them occaſion to fear what the Iſſue of this her ſeeming Phrenſy would be: So that having acquainted the Emperor with what Reſolutions ſhe had ſhut her ſelf up in her Lodging; the eaſy <hi>Diocleſian</hi> could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear going to her, that he might endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to aleviate her Sorrows, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the ſad Miſchief which her Retirement threatned. And here it may not be amiſs a little to conſider the Artifices of a Malicious, and Implacable Woman, and with what ſubtilties they ſeek the accompliſhment of their helliſh enterprizes. Nothing was more in the Mouth of this wicked Queen, than a ſence of the great violence offered to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51812:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the King: the extream danger of his Royal Perſon; and that for her own part, ſhe had no value for her own Life, farther than to ſeek, and endeavour the Safety of his Imperial Majeſty: ſuch expreſſions as theſe, were ever now and then the Accents of her Sorrow: when alas, nothing was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally leſs in her heart, but that ſhe might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain awaken the Rage of the too credulous Monarch, ſhe refreſhes his Memory with a Story of a certain <hi>King of England,</hi> who having given himſelf wholly to Pleaſure, and the Allurements of Debauchery; and delivered the Care of his People to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Seven Councellors; they, on the other ſide, were ſo addicted to their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs; that the common Iuſtice was turned into Wormwood; Extortion, Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Oppreſſion, taking place of Equity, and Reaſon. Now, as this Prince had wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blinded himſelf in Matters of State, by putting Confidence in ſuch evil Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the Iuſtice of Heaven deprived him of the uſe of his natural Eyes; ſo that, if at any time he went out of the Gates of the City, he became perfectly blind: This was ſo great an Affliction to the wretched King, that he ſought all probable means for Cure, but finding none; at length, he had notice of a ſtrange natural Magician, or Prophet, by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:51812:31"/> name <hi>Merlin,</hi> born in the Territories of his own Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> to whom, having applied himſelf for advice, he had from him an aſtoniſhing Relation of ſome Magical Balls that continually were burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing underneath the Ground, over which, his Royal Chamber and Bed ſtood: ſo that, until theſe Balls could be extinguiſhed, there was no hope of Cure for this Princes blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Whereupon the Celler being ſearched, there was found underneath the Pavement, the likeneſs of a Cauldren, wherein were ſeven burning Balls, exactly to the number of his ſeven State Miniſters or Inglers, one of them being bigger than the reſt. The King finding this ſtrange Relation of <hi>Merlin</hi> to be ſo far true, Councelled with him, how they might be extinguiſhed, and the Malignity of their Influence prevented.</p>
               <p>Know then Mighty Prince (ſaid <hi>Merlin</hi>) that theſe ſeven Balls are your ſeven Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, to whom you have committed the Management of the great Affairs of your Kingdom; and as long as you ſuffer theſe to live, the Balls will not ceaſe to burn, nor can your Sight return unto you: but if Your Majeſty make tryal by taking off the head of the chief of them, you will find that the great Ball will be dead and extinct; and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of the reſt. Whereupon the King
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51812:32"/> ordered the Captain of his Guard to cut off the head of his greateſt or chief Miniſter of State, and immediately the great Ball diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeared: then gradually Lopping off the reſt, the Balls all vaniſhed, and the Charm ceaſed: The King returned to his perceptive Faculty, and the due exerciſe of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the great happineſs and ſatisfaction of all his People. Thus have I given Your Imperial Majeſty, a ſhort, but true Account of this Story of the famous <hi>Mirlin;</hi> and I fear Your Highneſs needs the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of ſuch a Prophet; for certainly, as long as you are managed by the Councils of theſe ſeven Maſters, Your Majeſty will be blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and infatuated in relation to your own welfare, and that of your Empire. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, although hitherto the humble Requeſt I have made to Your Imperial Maleſty, hath not had that Succeſs, as for your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Safety I only deſired: I hope your ſerious conſideration of the foregoing Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will at leaſt animate you to ſecure the Fame and Grandure of the excellent <hi>Diocleſian.</hi> Here a torrent of <hi>Crocadile</hi> Tears ſtopt her diſcourſe for ſome time; till gaining breath of her ſighs, ſhe added, But oh! Sir, be ſure firſt ſtrike at the great Ball, the miſchevious and diſloyal <hi>Eraſtus.</hi> How Powerful and Charming is the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51812:32"/> of a Womans Paſſion, eſpecially humour'd to the height, and between a pair of warm Sheets (for now you muſt know, the Vxorious <hi>Diocleſian</hi> had laid himſelf by her, on her Treacherous Bed.) What can he more a Devil, than a wicked Woman in a Curtain Conſult? Certainly it had that Operation on the eaſy old Man, that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain pronounced that moſt unjuſt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Sentence; and ordered the moſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and innocent Prince <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> to be Executed the next Morning.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:51812:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <p>ANd now let us a little caſt our Eyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Priſon, and pay a Viſit to the abuſed Prince in his Misfortunes. Here we ſee one of the greateſt Examples of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Chaſtity, Sentenced for no leſs than Inceſt, and a Rape: A Son, the moſt Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, Obedient, Dutiful, and Affectionate; Condemned for a Traytor, Diſobedient, Vndutiful; and void of natural Affection: And can the All-ſeeing Iuſtice behold this! Can the Gods ſee the Compleateſt Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances of their Divinity, Goodneſs, and Excellence, dreſt up in the Form of Devils, and Condemned for ſuch? All this by thoſe who really are what they would repreſent the Virtuous to be, As it is well expreſſed by a Poet:
<q>
                     <l>THey were ſo Ripe for Hell! Could ſhe delay,</l>
                     <l>Not Gape, and Swallow quick, her greedy Prey?</l>
                     <l>Could Earth indure</l>
                     <l>Their Footſteps? was the Air grown ſo impure,</l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:51812:33"/>
                     <l>To give them Breath? Could Heaven behold their Riot</l>
                     <l>With patient Eyes? or could the <hi>Gods</hi> be Quiet?</l>
                  </q> Yet had the Learning of this young Prince ſo Improv'd his Morals, that he Contemn'd the utmoſt, their Rage and Cruelty could impoſe upon him: Having learnt of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,</hi> that he was born a Mortal, and therefore muſt once Dye, He calmly expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it; ſubmitting the time and manner to the <hi>Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, in all appearance, it drew near; for the Emperors Commands were enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the greateſt Severity, and on Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of utmoſt Rigour, not to be delayed this Morning; which was the fourth time the moſt inhumane Sentence had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. To prevent this, the ſtudious <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcopos</hi> waited the firſt opening of the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace Gate; and having an Opportunity, got into the Royal Apartment among ſome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians that were come, to attend the Queen: And they underſtanding, by the Pages of the Chamber, that the great Satisfaction ſhe had received by the King's laſt Order, and concluding her Deſign now obtained, was fallen into a ſound Sleep, after the good Succeſs of her Night-endeavours; ſo there
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51812:34"/> being no farther occaſion of them there; they waited on the King, who was now with drawn into his Dreſſing-room: But quickly perceiving the good <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> and ſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his buſineſs; having diſcharged at him ſeveral Fire-balls from his wrathful Eyes at laſt, he thunders on him a volly of ſmall Shot, in bitter words, after this manner: Cannot (then) the Bars of my Pallace, my Guards, nor my Royal Diſpleaſure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect my Perſon from being haunted with theſe Phyloſophical Fiends? Impudent Dog, How durſt thou appear in our Preſence; whom thou, and thy infamous Crew have ſo much abuſed? was it not enough, that you rob'd me of my only Son, whom I delivered to your Care, with the uſe, both of his Tongue and Reaſon? Whom now by your Sorceries, you have deprived of both, and poiſon'd him with all manner of Vice: whom (for the Reverence ye ought to have to our Perſon; and the Regard to the Roman Empire) you ſhould have Inſtructed in the beſt Science of Honour, and Virtue. But as ye have ſought my Ruine, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Empire; be aſſured, yours is not far off: For, if our Iuſtice ſpare not our own Impious Son; think not that you, his Diabolical Tutors ſhall eſcape. During all this Storm, <hi>Enoſcopos</hi> ſtood like a Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:51812:34"/> of a Light-within-man before the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition: But the Tempeſt being ſomewhat over, and <hi>Diocleſian</hi> almoſt out of Breath; ſome of the Lords there preſent, who had long known the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> to be perſons that through the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld had acquired a vaſt ſtock of Reputation; and eſpecially that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman being preſent, who was ſent to fetch the Prince to Court, and had there heard a ſufficient proof of his excellent Acquirements. Theſe I ſay, miſtruſting ſome Monſtrous Intrigue in the bottom of this ſtrange Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, prevailed with the Emperor, That the Sage <hi>Philoſopher</hi> might have freedom to deliver the Maſſage that had brought him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. With much add he had Permiſſion, and with an unmov'd <hi>Athenian</hi> Face; but ſuch Majeſtick Gravity, as commanded Reverence, even from <hi>Diocleſian</hi> himſelf; <hi>Enoſcopos</hi> thus addreſt to the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GReat</hi> Prince, <hi>could the ſence of your mighty Diſpleaſure, or the fear of Death have afrighted me from the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of my Duty to your Majeſty; and thoſe great Obligations to common Juſtice: I had not at this time given Your Majeſty the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſo loath'd a Preſence. But ill doth he deſerve the name of a</hi> Philoſopher, <hi>that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers not his Adherence to Moral Virtue, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51812:35"/> the publick Good, beyond all the gay Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that deceived Mortals Idolize. Nor have I any reaſon to believe, that Humanity hath ſo far forſaken the Roman Emperor, but that he will permit a defence in the behalf of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; &amp; not ſuffer ſo rigid a Sentence to be put in Execution on the bare word of a weak; and perhaps deceitful Woman. And I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg Your Imperial Majeſty, not to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at the harſhneſs of the Expreſſion: And if you will this once more grant your Princely Remand of the Sentence againſt Prince</hi> Eraſtus, <hi>until I have, by infallible Demonſtration, convinced Your Majeſty, that in this affair, the greateſt Caution, and Circumſpection is moſt agreeable to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Roman Emperor: Then let me bear him Company in his Fate; and I ſhall, with all acknowledgment, for ſo great Clemency put my Head under your Royal Feet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperor touched with a Sence of Humanity, of which the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> had minded him; and being too, out of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>Aphrodicea;</hi> began ſomewhat to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and diſpatched a Meſſenger to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Guard, who was now on his way to the place of Execution, to return the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner again, till farther Order. In the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:51812:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> mean while Enoſcopos entertained the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror with this Relation.</p>
               <p>The unfortunate (becauſe credulous) Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander liv'd at Rodes, and was juſtly eſteemed one of the Wealthieſt, and moſt Honourable Inhabitants of that famous City: This per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being, by the Importunity and Advice of his Friends, Married to a Lady, whoſe Beauty, Fortune, and Family, ſpoke her no leſs Honourable; did, as is uſual among perſons of Quality, commit the management of all Houſhold Affairs to the Conduct of his Lady: who having with her a Maid-ſervant, that had always waited on her at School, and of whoſe Fidelity and Wit ſhe had a very good Opinion; therefore ſhe intruſted her, mainly, with the overſight of the other Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. This Girl being young and wanton, out of her Ladys ſight, had one day got into her Embraces a young Lad of the Family; and this Lady, by accident, took them in the very Act: whereupon being much ſurprized, that her Woman (in whom ſhe had the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Confidence imaginable) ſhould, by her wantonneſs, pull ſo great a diſhonour on her Husbands Houſe: She was once of the mind to have told her Lord of it; but fearing, leſt his reſentment or ſo foul an Act might have too far inflamed his paſſion, and have urged him to ſome Violencies, that afterwards might have reflected to his preiudice. She, poor Lady, endeavoured, for that time, to conceal the Fault of her Servant; but ſuffered it not to eſcape without her own moſt juſt Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:51812:36"/> for immediately ſhe turned the Fellow out of doors, and having ſoundly Rated and Corrected her Maid, ſhe permitted her ſtill to all the ſame place in her Family; hoping ſo gentle a Chaſtiſement might work her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. But alas! the ſad effect of baſe Ingratitude, and the Rage of diſappointed Luſt; nothing certainly is more implacable than a Strumpet, balkt in the enjoyment of her inordinate Pleaſures: This will appear by the ſequel of my Story, which I ſhall as much as poſſible abreviate.</p>
               <p>This deteſtable Slut, although her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Miſtreſs, had laid on her the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation Your Majeſty hath heard; ſtudied nothing from that time, but to Revenge the Loſs of her looſe Pleaſures, with the Loſs of the Life of that moſt Virtuous and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Lady: And accordingly, one After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, when her Miſtreſs was diverting her ſelf in the Garden, with ſome other Ladies; her Maſter alone reading in the Parlour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhe takes this opportunity to inſinuate into his belief the moſt incredible Falſehood i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the World; but having long deliberate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how to varniſh and diſguiſe it; ſhe thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan her Treaſons.</p>
               <p>Sir, I moſt humbly crave Pardon of your Honour for this, my bold, intruſion into your Privacy; and withal, I earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51812:36"/> you to believe nothing but the hearty Zeal I have for your Happineſs, and juſt ſatisfaction could have put me upon it: This you will have, all the reaſon in the world to believe, when you perceive, that I, who have ever been bred up at the Feet of your Lady; I, who ſo particularly ſhare in her extraordinary Favour, and that can hope for no happineſs, but what her Benevolence imparts to me; that even I am compelled by the obligations I owe to Virtue; not to ſee ſo excellent a Perſon, ſo good a Maſter as your ſelf, in the higheſt meaſure Abuſed. And therefore, with the greateſt Violence to my own Circumſtances, I come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to you that Secret, which I much fear will Tranſport you into ſome extraordinary Violence to your ſelf; you having a long time had the misfortune to have been abuſed by one of the moſt Treacherous of Woman-kind. This Sir, is that which hath made my Food unpleaſant, and my Sleep full of diſtraction; when I conſider, that a Perſon of her excellent Endowments, extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Education, moſt reputed Virtue; ſhould lay aſide the Regard ſhe ought to have to her own Honour, the happineſs, the ſatisfaction of the moſt incomparable Husband in the World; and ſuffer her ſelf to be debauched by a Boy that lives by the meaneſt drudgeries
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51812:37"/> of the houſe: Here ſhe was ſtopt in her Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer, by the half diſtracted <hi>Cleander;</hi> who had long before this, torn any other Tongue, that had been guilty but of half theſe Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, out of the curſt Traducers Throat; but conſidering the Relation this wench ſtood in to his Lady, and her entire dependance upon her Favour; he was ſo miſerably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, as to give her leave to go on with her divelliſh Narrative; which ſhe did to this manner: The Gods are witneſs how oft, and with how earneſt ſupplication I have, on my Knees, pray'd her not to defile ſo Sacred a Tye, as the Holy Prieſt had joyn'd her in, with ſo unworthy a proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her excellent Perſon, and violating her Obligations to the beſt of Husbands But it hath been my unhappineſs to beat the Air, and all the Succeſs my unwearied En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours have met with, have been, my ſelf to be beaten; of which, I think ſome of the Marks yet remain. So that, ſeeing ſhe hath laid aſide all ſence of ſhame, and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: I could not poſſibly reſt, until I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcharged my Conſcience in making known a practiſe ſo diſloyal and brutiſh unto your ſelf; that by ſuch means, as ſhall be moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Reaſon, and the innate Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Humanity, you may endeavour yet to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim her from utter Ruine and Perdition.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:51812:37"/> But I moſt earneſtly beg of your Honour, not to ſeem to take any notice hereof, until I have given you an Ocular Demonſtration of what I have now related.</p>
               <p>Ye Gods! ſaid <hi>Cleander:</hi> and is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo excellent Beauty and Sweetneſs, can harbour a Soul ſo Deformed and Divelliſh! Oh! moſt unfortunate <hi>Cleander:</hi> Could the Fates mark out no one to make the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their utmoſt Violence and Injury, but unhappy thee? A miſerable Man. But perceiving the Ladies coming in from the Garden, he ſent out the wench, ordering her to take no notice of what had paſt: and put himſelf into the beſt poſture he could to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them. Which he did, with the beſt diſſembled Countenance that poſſible he could; ſo that it happened no notice was taken of the diſorder he was in. From this time, his great care was to mark, and obſerve all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages betwixt his poor innocent Wife, and her reputed Paramour, who was a Boy, Son to a Tennant of his Ladies Father, and having ever been bred up in the Family, was very dilligent in obſerving his Maſters and Miſtreſs Commands; Every caſt of an Eye was attended on by the officious <hi>Henry</hi> (for that was his name) who little thought how dearly he was, in a ſhort time, to Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the honeſt Teſtimonies of his Fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:51812:38"/> But not a geſture or motion, though never ſo innocent; and that before, paſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as inſtances, honeſt dilligence; but now, by the Eyes of Iealouſy, were repreſented wanton, and as having a Laſcivious ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: Inſomuch, that this Humour rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and being fomented in the Heart of the wretched <hi>Cleander;</hi> it rendred him incapable of receiving any real Satisfaction in any thing. Therefore he determined now to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a final Conſult with his Helliſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant, how to have this Oculer Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, upon which, he reſolved immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to diſpatch the Objects of his Rage: She ſoon told him, That if he only took his Cane and Gloves, and pretended a viſit for three or four hours time, and then made a ſhort turn in the ſpace of an hour, ſhe would not fall to be as good as her word; provided he only came in at the door (which ſhe would leave open) without knocking, and ſtraight repair to his Chamber. To which he having conſented; and told his poor innocent Lady that he was going to ſee ſome Friends, from whom he ſhould not return untill the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; putting on his Rapier, he trent forth, taking no Servant with him. The tender Lady perceiving her Husband gone forth, and having obſerved of late, a Cloud to ſit on that Brow, that always was wont to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:51812:38"/> be ſerene and clear; being ſome what indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed went to her Chamber, and lay on her Bed, to Sigh away a fit of Melancholly, Now was the curſed Maid to play her Game, which ſhe did in this manner: Having (as ſhe was Governeſs of the Houſe) comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the poor diſtruſtleſs Page to get up into his Chamber, and exerciſe himſelf in his Writing; ſhe had now Lodged her Prey, and was ready, as ſoon as ſhe could diſcern the Abuſed <hi>Cleander</hi> coming home, to ſend him into her Ladies Chamber. This ſhe had ſoon occaſion to do, for perceiving her Maſter at hand, ſhe calls <hi>Henry;</hi> you muſt preſently go to your Miſtreſs, who hath an Errand to ſend you in: The poor Lad diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches to his Ladies Chamber; where ſhe having given an account, that ſhe call'd him not, his Maſter met him juſt coming out of the door; and ſeeing his Lady on the bed; without farther Examination, immediately runs him through; of which, he preſently dyed: then dragging the amazed Lady to the ſame place, he caſt her on the Page, and ſent them together to <hi>Eliſium.</hi> Thus were two Innocents moſt barbarouſly Murthered, a moſt Honourable Family deſtroyed, and all by the over-credulous Raſhneſs of <hi>Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> who having the bare Suggeſtion of a depraved and malicious Slut, moſt cruelly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:51812:39"/> Butcher'd the moſt Loyal, Spotleſs, and Indulgent Wife in the World; and ſent a Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>leſs Page to attend her Ghoſt. Theſe Royal Sir, are the effects of miſguided Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and blind Iuſtice; that ſtrikes the blow without conſidering the Equity of the Cauſe. Let it ſuffice, that <hi>Cleander</hi> afterward ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deſtroy'd his Peace, had this Helliſh Wench on the Rack, which Confeſſing the whole Truth in his preſence, he immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut out her Heart, and Stab'd himſelf; falling a Sacrifice to his own remedileſs Raſhneſs: And thereby giving occaſion for this <hi>Epitaph,</hi> which afterward was ſet on his Tomb.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="epitaph">
                           <head>Cleanders Epitaph.</head>
                           <l>THis Marble Weeps wretched <hi>Cleanders</hi> Fate;</l>
                           <l>Who ſaw his blinded Phrenſy, when too late:</l>
                           <l>And vainly fell his Fault to Expiate.</l>
                           <l>Reader, beware of Femal's treacherous Tales,</l>
                           <l>Learn hence the dire Event, when Reaſon fails;</l>
                           <l>And blind, raſh Paſſion Impiouſly prevails.</l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Thus Royal Sir, have I given Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty the Relation of this Famous Story of <hi>Padua,</hi> on which, if you pleaſe ſeriouſly to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:51812:39"/> reflect, you will find it very pertinent to the great Affair now in debate. Here was a ſoul Crime charged on thoſe that underſtood nothing but Innocence; a forward, and eaſy miſtruſt, grounded on a Malicious Slander, &amp; that vouched but by one Witneſs: the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence whereof was an Act of Indelive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, &amp; unparallel'd Cruelty, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ended in the Deſtruction of an Honourable Family: But what would not the Knight have given, when he once underſtood his Irreparable Errour? what would he not have ſuffered, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieved his Loſs, and the Murther of two Innocents? But 'twas too late, the fatal Blow was given; and that Sword that had been ſtained in the Blood of the Guiltleſs, by the ſame hand Revenged it on the Guilty. I need make no farther Remarks on the Alluſion of the Circumſtances, where ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Wiſdom is preſent, as could dive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to much abſtrucer points. If what I have ſaid avail to the Advantage of the excellent <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> ſo that a raſh Sentence may not paſs againſt him, without the Debate of a full Senate, which is moſt Conſonant to the Honour, and Grandure of the Potent'ſt Emperor in the World: I have then the Anſwer of my Prayers. Thus, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Gravity, the Famous <hi>Enoſcopos</hi> ended tis Learned Oration: Which wrought ſo
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51812:40"/> effectually, both on the Emperor, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Senate there preſent; that for that day his Requeſt was granted.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>THe Emperor (as was ſaid) having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled with the Requeſt of the Learned <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> at the inſtance of the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; and finding that he ſhould always be vexed with the Queens Importunities, whilſt he continued in the ſame Pallace with her, Removed to a Caſtle he had about eighteen
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51812:40"/> Miles out of the City; leaving Orders with his Senators, that they ſhould in the mean time Debate the Affair of the Prince; and Act therein, as was agreeable to the Iuſtice of the Empire.</p>
               <p>But who can think ſo eaſily to Evade the Crafts of an implacable Woman: As the Poet Sings:
<q>
                     <l>So hard it is, where an old Grutch is</l>
                     <l>To get out of a Womans Clutches.</l>
                  </q> For no ſooner had <hi>Aphrodicea</hi> underſtood of the King's Progreſs, which was taken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her privity; but though ſhe had met with four Defeats of her Serpentine wiles: She reſolved to attempt the Fifth; intending that her Pen ſhould make a deeper Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, than poſſible her words could before: Therefore entring her Cloſet, and dropping ſome of the Verjuice of her Eyes into her Standiſh; ſhe wrote a Letter to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to this effect.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Letter.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THough, contrary to the Laws of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Your Royal Contract, you have Conveyed your ſelf from your Pallace, without permitting the Unfortunate <hi>Aphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea</hi>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:51812:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> to know of your Removal: Yet Your Majeſty may be aſſured the Walls of your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle will prove too Weak a Fence againſt the Batteries of my Juſt Importunities. Does any Story mention an Emperor (who ought to be the Standard of Juſtice) that ſhould four times violate his Sacred Promiſe, and that upon one and the ſame Occaſion: And eſpecially, when for ought we know, his Life (or at leaſt his Honour, that ought to be much dearer) is ſo viſibly Expoſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? How ill doth the Soveraign Diadem ſet on her Brow, that is denied the Birth-right of the meaneſt Vaſſal in <hi>Rome.</hi> Remember <hi>(Diocleſian)</hi> I ſay remember the Burning <hi>Balls!</hi> But if you are ſtill reſolved to be led by the Noſe by a parcel of Thred-bare <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers:</hi> I will once more enter my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial againſt your irregular Proceedings, and Relate to Your Majeſty, what happened to a great Treaſurer of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Who having a Riotous young Extravagant to his Son; the too Indulgent Father took care forſooth, to breed him up in the Study of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and to that end committed him to the Care of ſuch another crew of worthy Tutors, as you diſpoſed your Son unto: Theſe, in ſhort time, made even with the good old Man's Eſtate, and reduced him to ſuch a ſtate of Poverty, that he had not longer where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51812:41"/> to ſubſiſt: Therefore calling his young <hi>Philoſopher</hi> to Council, he adviſed with him, what were beſt to be done to Conceal the ſhame of his Poverty from the World. The Lad having ſufficiently been Trained up in the ſcience of Miſchief, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth his Father to make ſome ſecret Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage under Ground, in at the Foundation of a certain Tower, where the Treaſure of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Kings was kept, and that from thence, they might privately ſupply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as often as Need required: Preſent Neceſſity made every thing ſeem probable that preſented it ſelf; and therefore, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out farther debate, the old Treaſurer ſets upon the Enterprize, with his graceleſs Son; who having found a Cave, not far from the Tower Wall, that formerly had been the Habitation of a <hi>Hermit;</hi> they, through one ſide of this Vault, ſoon wrought Acceſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Treaſure: But the Crany being of ſo ſmall Dimention, that one Man could hardly, and with much difficulty enter it: The Father made a ſhift to put himſelf in thereat, and conveyed thence ſo great a quantity of Gold, as for a long time Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Port of their Family. In ſhort, this Store was likewiſe ſpent, and a ſecond Adventure muſt be made for a farther Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply: The poor old Man once more puts
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:51812:42"/> himſelf into the Bilbo's, but not with ſuch Succeſs as before: For by this time the Keepers of the Tower had diſcovered, that ſome of the Treaſure had been conveyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and as they ſuppoſed by means of that Crevice, which they obſerved in the Wall: Therefore, that they might make ſure of their Prey, they fixed there ſo Artificial a Gin, that whoſoever was once got in, could by no means eſcape there-from with Life: This the old Treaſurer ſoon perceived (for he was taken in the Toyl) and it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the young Man to bring him off alive; he moſt unnaturally put an end to that Life that had given him his; by taking off his Fathers Head: Which he did, that the Officers not knowing the Body, the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Family might eſcape that Severity, that otherwiſe the Law would have inflicted on them, for an Offence ſo heinous. But his Wickedneſs ended not here, for return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home, and knowing his Mother had been privy to the Theft; doubting her weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might ſome time or other betray the Treaſon, he moſt inhumanly knockt her on the Head. Here Mighty Prince, you have a plain Demonſtration of what muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from a Son Educated amongſt <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers:</hi> They only wait to ſee you in the Snare, and you will ſoon fare as the old
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:51812:42"/> Treaſurer; and as for me, I ſhall ſoon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you in Fate; which indeed is the only Conſideration that affords me any Comfort. For what Pleaſure is it poſſible the wretched <hi>Aphrodicea</hi> can be capable of, after the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the unwary <hi>Diocleſian.</hi> What ſhall I ſay my Dear Lord? muſt I then be the Contempt of the whole World, whilſt For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes deride; and my own Subjects deſpiſe my Misfortune? I have taken the boldneſs thus once more to caſt my ſelf at Your Royal Feet, not doubting, but your Natural Inclinations to the Common Juſtice, will not permit you any longer to deny a due Reparation to the Honour of the moſt Unfortunate</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Aphrodicea.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Letter having Signed with her privy Signet, ſhe gave to one of her Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to be ſpeedily delivered to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; which accordingly being performed: <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> at the peruſal of it, was like one at the violent return of a Feavor Fit; for though his abſence from her perpetual Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, had procured him a tollerable good Settlement of Mind, and the Fervor of his Paſſion intermitted; yet as ſoon as he had peruſed this Paper, it preſently ſet him all in a Flame. So that immediately calling
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51812:43"/> for Pen and Ink, he, with his own Hand, wrote an Order to the Captain of his Guard, to deal with <hi>Eraſtus</hi> according to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>Aphrodicea;</hi> for that he had wholly put that Affair under her Determination: And Sealing it with his Royal Signet, he ſent it back by the ſame Meſſenger.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <p>BVt as theſe things could not be ſo ſecretly managed, but that the <hi>Sages</hi> had Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence thereof: The tender <hi>Philantropus,</hi> who was to Obviate the Fifth Sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:51812:43"/> the moſt Innocent Prince; very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Morning preſſing through the Guards, who had great veneration for him; and perhaps ſome regard to the preſervation of the moſt to be Lamented <hi>Eraſtus:</hi> It mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not much upon what occaſion, but the reſolute <hi>Philoſopher</hi> having got to the Royal Preſence (depending perhaps on the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Stars) he gave not leave to the Emperor, to muſter up his Paſſion, by the uſual method of telling him his reſentments, or diſpleaſure; but to prevent the gathering of that Storm, He preſently throws him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on the Ground, and in a poſture that te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed the greateſt tranſport of extream Sorrow: He began with moſt admirable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence to bewail the Ruin, both of the Emperor, and the Empire, in a Language ſo Charming, ſo vigorous force of Reaſon; that <hi>Diocleſian</hi> himſelf thought nothing leſs than Marble could be unmoved at it. What, ſaid the compaſſionate <hi>Philantropus,</hi> and is it the inevitable Misfortune of Crown'd Heads to be thus prejudiced, and blinded by the moſt inhumane, cruel, barbarous, and perfidious Sex! Cannot the Sacred Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, nor the Intereſt of the Empire (in which their own is concerned) prevent this Blanket-Dominion? Sad Fate of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy! Conſider moſt Excellent Emperor;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:51812:44"/> but what it is you have Signed, and at whoſe Inſtance; and you will doubtleſs ſee the greateſt Reaſon in the World, to retract a Determination ſo directly oppoſite to your own Royal Intereſt, and the Honour of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. Muſt the moſt Illuſtrious, and only Branch of your Princely Stock; the only Hope of the Empire; the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, and greateſt Example of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Virtue, be Sacrifized to the Luſt, Mallice, and Deſigns of an inſatiate Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? The moſt Soveraign Iuſtice of the Gods forbid it! One would have thought, the ſad Inſtances my Brethren had given Your Majeſty of the Conſtant Treachery of that Sex, might at leaſt have tyed Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to your Promiſe of having the Matter debated in full Senate! Which I am apt to believe, would ſound much more for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Diocleſian</hi>'s Iuſtice, and the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate, than thus raſhly; and, as it were, by your own Hand, to cut off one, whom the Gods have deſtin'd to give Laws to Mankind; and not only Subjugate Kingdoms, but Hearts to the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoak. I ſhall only make bold to refreſh your Royal Remembrance, with one or two Stories of the Subtilty, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matcht Cruelty of Womankind; that when you have taken a view of them in their own
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:51812:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> Actions; you may be the better Induced not to comply with their Flatteries. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what I am going to ſay, is ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally known, I ſhall give Your Imperial Majeſty the leſs trouble; and will only give a hint. The firſt ſhall be of Cleander; whoſe unchaſt Wife frequenting Night De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches, whilſt her Husband was Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing to Morpheus; ſhe had blinded his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect with frequent Excuſes for her abſence, which was often perceived by her Husband, and he, as often, had his Credulity Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on, by her ſophiſtical Shams and Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. But one Night, having a more than ordinary miſtruſt, he goes down out of his Bed, and makes the Door faſt on the inſide; which the looſe Harlot perceiving, at her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from her night ramble, made many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties to her Husband to open the Door, that ſhe might not be Apprehended by the Watch: For ſuch was the ſtrictneſs of that City, that whoſoever was taken by them in their Rounds, were moſt Ignomiouſly expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Publick, for Perſons incontinent, and vitious Livers: The old Man thinking this little Severity might Correct the head of her Inclinations, ſeemed to defer giving her Admittance, and would have wrought her into a Promiſe of Reformation: When the ſubtle Courtezan ran to a Well there adjoyning; and caſting in a great Stone, made the over-credulous Husband believe, that ſhe had thrown her ſelf into it; whilſt indeed ſhe only convey'd her ſelf behind the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:51812:45"/> Porch: The poor Husband runs to the Well like a Man in diſtraction, calling on his Wife; and letting down the Bucket, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to preſerve her from periſhing; curſing himſelf, that he had ſo much urged on her patience, to bring her to ſo miſerable and ſhameful an end. In fine, the Man having tired himſelf with fruitleſs Lamentations, &amp; being almoſt ſtarved with cold, having only his Shirt on; and now concluding his Wife buried in the Water, was in great Sorrow returning to his Bed, when, to his great Surprizal he found the Door ſhut againſt him. What ſhall I ſay? It was now the implacable Fiend's part to play; which ſhe did to purpoſe; for a thouſand importunities, and proteſtations of the truth of his Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions could not prevail with her; ſhe was deaf to all, kept him in the ſtreet till the Watch came, and there Accuſed the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent old Man of Ribaldry, and Incontinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the Officers; charging, and loading him with a thouſand Crimes that he knew not of. Thus was this Abuſed Man carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a cold Priſon, and having paſſed the Night in incredible Miſery, was he next day ſet in the Pillory to the great Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Citizens, who had known him a Perſon of a long, and unblemiſh. Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Thus was the ſhameleſs Harlot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Triumph in her Diabolical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge on her Honeſt and Immaculate Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; here is Female Craft and Mallice to the height exalted: The Moral of which, I
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:51812:45"/> ſhall humbly ſubmit to your moſt Serene Majeſties Conſideration; not doubting but it may produce in Your Royal Breaſt, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of Relinguiſhing the Influences of that Treacherous Sex And I ſhall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crave Your Princely Pardon to refer the Recital of my other Inſtance to the next Chapter.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <p>THe Emperor being ſomewhat wrought upon by the former Relation of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantropus was very Attentive for the ſecond; which the Philoſopher thus began. Should I, moſt Mighty Emperor, undertake to ſet
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:51812:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> out the Frauds of evil Women, time would fail me, for there is no end of their Treachery; however, I ſhall make one ſhort Inſtance more to confirm what I have Aſſerted: It is ſaid, The Governor of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco</hi> had a Wife ſo Fair, that he feared the Power of her Beauty would make Priſe of all ſhe looked on; to prevent which, he prepared a very rich Apartment for her in a Tower he had ſtanding in a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs near his Palace, the Cituation of it was exceeding Pleaſant, ſtanding amongſt Groves of Mirtle, and Fountains of moſt Admirable Work: nor wonted it the moſt rich and ſplendid Lining, for Guilding, Painting, Tapeſtry, curious Beds, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Plate, with Aviaries of moſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodious Birds, that made the Air Eccho with their warbling Muſick: She had Maids and Eunuchs in very rich Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to Attend her; and was Carreſſed with all the Charming Daliances of a King's Miſtreſs. Yet amongſt all theſe Splendid Entertainments, ſhe was Vnpleaſant, Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and Vnſatisfied; for the Governor himſelf kept the Key of this Enchanted Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, never permitting her to come forth, but on ſome particular dayes; and that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his own Preſence; nor admitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the ſight of her but her own Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:51812:46"/> before-mentioned. Yet it ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, that one day at a Tilting, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor having ſet her by him under a rich Pavillion, ſhe was obſerved by a young Lord of <hi>Greece,</hi> who, at firſt ſight, took the <hi>Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy</hi> to her Beauty; and after performing things beyond the power of belief in Honour of her: But it was a long time, and coſt him many a tireſome Night before he could un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how it was poſſible for him to let her underſtand his Paſſion; till at laſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving underſtood of her ſtrict Confinement to this Tower, he took a Houſe of a great Courtiers, who was gone beyond Sea on an Embaſy; which Houſe ſtood void, and on one ſide of this pleaſant Wilderneſs: So that having Furniſhed his new Houſe very Richly, and fallen into ſome Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Governor, whom he often Treated with a Magnificence, more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to a great Prince, than a private No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-man; he began to conſider how he might accompliſh his Project, and Arrive to the Enjoyment of the Adored Idea of his Love: Conſulting therefore the moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Windows of his Lodging; he at laſt obſerved a Caſement that fronted directly over a Walk to the Window of this Recluſes Cloſet: So that ſometimes by
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:51812:47"/> the advantage of the Sun, he could ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to her, and obſerve her G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſture (w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich as yet was all the Language that paſſed) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. To be ſhort, it was come thus far, that when a Roſe was ſhewed out at his Window, another would peep out of hers; if he ſometimes with his Looking G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſs Darted the Sun-Beams into her Cloſet, ſhe would give his Chamber a Reflection of the ſame Divertiſement; ſo that now there wanted nothing but a nearer Acceſs to their being inwardly Acquainted. In order to this, a way was found to dig a paſſage from a Vault under his Houſe, through the Foundation of the Governors Garden-wall; which being well managed, obtained a Secret Entrance at the Root of a great Pepler Tree, ſtanding, by a Brook, in a very obſcure part of the Wilderneſs: This Tree being hollow, proved the moſt Advantagious to the furtherance of their Deſigns imaginable. For one Evening, obſerving the Coaſt to be clear, and his Saint at her Window-devotion, he fixed a Paper to the end of a Thread, &amp; gently let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſlide out at the Caſement, would, in her ſight, draw it up again; ſo that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeating the Signal, ſhe became in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, That it would be needful for her to hang a Thread to her cloſet Window;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:51812:47"/> which having done, our young Gallant took the occaſion to paſs through his Loop hole, and faſten a French guilded Paper (ſealed with perfumed Wax, having the Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a wounded Heart) to the end of the ſtring: So the Fiſh having took the Hook, was ſoon Landed in the Fair Hand of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Lady, who having opened it, found therein theſe Verſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HOw unhappy a Lover am I!</l>
                     <l>Thus to Sigh for my <hi>Phili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s</hi> in Vain,</l>
                     <l>All my hope of Delight, is another Mans Right,</l>
                     <l>Who is Happy, whilſt I am in Pain.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But were the vaſt Rocks thy ſtrong Tower,</l>
                     <l>I would rend their tough Cement in ſunder,</l>
                     <l>And force my dear Saint from her Bower,</l>
                     <l>Or I'd borrow of <hi>Vulcane</hi> his Thunder.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>She having read this Rapture, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed all thoſe Solemnities to the Paper, that Love-Sick Nimphs are wont, took an occaſion to drop another in return, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide whereof contained this:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Have no Vein in Poetry, and therefore muſt crave leave to thank you for your extraordinary Paſſion in Proſe; and that I may the ſooner have an opportunity to do
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:51812:48"/> it, do you wear the incloſed Signet in my Husbands preſence, and with all poſſible ſpeed let me have it again: If the project take, you may in ſhort time make me the happy, who am now the Unfortunate</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Cloe.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Tranſported <hi>Greek</hi> having received this firſt Pledge of her Affection, laid it next his Heart, and making a hundred Cringes to his Idol, haſted through his <hi>Conny-berry,</hi> to underſtand the Pleaſure of his Goddeſs. He had no ſooner read it, but on goes the Ring, and the guilt Coach is immediately made ready; not a Page but had his beſt Embroidered Livery: in this Equipage, two ſtately white <hi>Flanders</hi> Mares rattle him to the Gate of the Court, where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving underſtood, that the Governor was at a Gaming Ordinary at the other end of the Town, he orders his Coach to drive thither; and going into the Room, after paſſing the uſual Complements, the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles were took in hand, and conſequently the Ring diſplaid it ſelf to the Eye of the Governor; who being much ſurprized with Apprehenſion, that it was a Ring he had given his Lady; and ſuſpecting that it might be Feloniouſly come by, was almoſt at his Wits end; his Countenance changed,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:51812:48"/> his Breath grew ſhort, and he was very near falling into a Swoon; but at laſt, conſidering that it might be a miſtake, he made enquiry of the young Grecian, where that Ring might have been bought; who returning, that it had been given him by his Father: The Governor, at that time, made no farther Appearance of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uneaſy. Some Guinnies having been got and loſt between the Gamſters, and plenty of Bottles emptied; the Grecian took leave of the Governor, leaving him in company with ſome Nobles, who intended to paſs the reſt of the Night in a Ball. In the mean time, our Tower-Lady ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing on but a Damask night Gown, was at her poſt, expecting the Reſult of her Lovers Enterprize: And it was not long e're, by the Moon-light, ſhe percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her good Angel under the Window; who having faſtned the Ring to the Thread, gave his Miſtreſs a fair opportunity to make the beſt of her Stratagem on the deluded Governor; which ſhe did in this manner: For he was no ſooner returned the next Morning to his Pallace, but immediately he makes to his Ladies Chamber, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſuſpected Ring on her Finger; withal, obſerving the exact Reſemblance in all things, between that, and what he
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:51812:49"/> had lately ſeen on the young Lords Hand; it put him upon ſome ſtrange Conſiderations, which occaſioned a more than ordinary Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly on his Fore-head. The Lady, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the true method of Woman-craft, taking notice thereof; and being ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly inquiſitive of the cauſe of it: After he had, with ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me pretences, excus'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; at length acknowledged he had been ſurprized to ſee a Ring ſo (in all things) alike hers, worn by a Gentleman of his Acquaintance; but withal, told her, That he was ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sfied they might both be made by one and the ſame Work-man. Nay Sir, replied the Gipſy, you will have but little reaſon to wonder at a reſemblance of this kind in things Inanimate, which may be formed to any figure, or proportion the Arteſt pleaſeth, for, if I am not miſinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, there is lately Arrived at the young Grecian Lords Houſe, a Lady much reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling my ſelf, who hath a little Dog ſo like mine, that it is impoſſible to know them one from the other: That is ſomewhat ſtrange, ſaid the Governor; but I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſatisfy my ſelf in that point, in a little time. In ſhort, this was but an Artifice of the Womans, the ſooner to accompliſh the Enjoyment of her Adored Grecian: So that as ſoon as the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:51812:49"/> had left her, ſhe gave the ſignal, and dropt a Note out of her Window, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng what you may read in the following diſcourſe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>THe Plot of the Ring hath ſo well Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, that if you can procure a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Convey you into your own Country; I have laid a Deſign that will infallibly give you the opportunity of taking me along with you; for as ſoon as I have Notice that a Yeſſel is ready, I will convey my ſelf by the Window, which is toward the private Paſſage you have made into your Lodging; and there put ſuch a Device in Execution, as ſhall not fail to Accompliſh our Mutual Deſires. In the mean time, be ſure, as ſoon as you have ſecured a Veſſel, Invite the Governor to Dine with you the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Eraſpe.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>For that was the then Queen of <hi>Moroc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi>'s Name. The Grecian preſently got to the Port, and finding there one of the Gallys of his own Country newly Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he hired it for his Service, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Men to be in readineſs the next Morning, to put to Sea as he ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:51812:50"/> them. This being diſpatched, he preſently Applies himſelf to the King, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting him, That upon ſome Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Notice he had lately received from his own Country, he muſt crave his Majeſties leave to depart, and inveſt himſelf with a principallity lately fallen to him; and that a Veſſel was ready in the Port to attend him. Only he prayed the King, that, for the many Favours he had confer'd upon him, it would pleaſe his Highneſs to accept of a Dinner with him the day following; which the good King accepting, and withal, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying great Sorrow for the Loſs of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he had ſo great a Value for. As for this <hi>Grecian</hi> Prince, they parted for that time: this being ſoon ſignified to the Queen, ſhe put all things in readineſs for the next Morning; giving Notice to her Paramour, That he ſhould expect her at the Foot of the Pepler Tree in the Garden. The King in the Morning, conſidering he was that day to Dine with, and take his leave of his great Favorite the young <hi>Grecian</hi> Lord, went early to ſee the Queen, and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her, he was to Dine abroad that day, and that ſhe was not to expect him untill the Evening: from thence, he went to the Council-Chamber, to give Order for the diſpatches of that day. He had no ſooner
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:51812:50"/> left the Queen, but ſhe placing her ſelf, and her Dog in a Basket, faſtened by a little Pully on the outſide of the Window, and holding by the Cord, gently let her ſelf down into the Garden; and by the young Lord was conveyed through the private Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage into his Lodging; and being got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hiss Cloſet, with his help, was put into the Habit of a <hi>Grecian</hi> Lady, richly Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with coſtly Iewels; and the Plot laid, that the young <hi>Grecian</hi> was to Affirm her to be a Sweet-heart of his, in their own Country; who, for Love of him, had come over the Sea to Marry him. Things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus ordered; at laſt comes the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, with ſome of his Nobles, to take their Farewel of the Famous young <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Lord; who having received them, with all imaginable demonſtrations of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry; at laſt, expreſſed himſelf to the King after this manner.</p>
               <p>Mighty Prince, ſince my coming to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco,</hi> I have daily had ſuch Experience of your Royal Goodneſs and Favour; that I eſteem my poor Life too mean an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement for ſuch high Obligations. But ſince a Royal Patrimony in <hi>Greece</hi> calls for me; and here is lately Arrived a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſingular Quality and Perfection, who, being bred up with me, hath ſought me in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:51812:51"/> divers Courts, and is reſolved, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Love of my Perſon, to run all Hazard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in my company. Therefore I am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, before I go to the Gally, to Celebra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Hymeneal</hi> Rights; and if it pleaſe You<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Majeſty to give her to me in Marriage with Your Royal Hand, I ſhall receive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as the greateſt Adition to your Princel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Favours. The good King was eaſily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with, to comply with any thing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> might teſtify his great Reſpects to the youn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Grecian;</hi> eſpecially in a matter of this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance: So that the young Lord immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately leading his Lady into the Room where the Princes of <hi>Morocco</hi> were; they were, on the ſudden, much ſurprized at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appearance of ſo excellent Beauty, ſo ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly Adorned: the King, the more he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on her, fancying he ſaw his own Queen but that the Secureneſs of his Tower, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the diſcourſe his Wife had made to him o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Lady at this <hi>Grecians</hi> Lodging, that had ſo great Reſemblance with her; beſides th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> likeneſs of the Kings. Theſe things run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in his thoughts, fixed, in his imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the ſtrongeſt conceit of reſemblance, and parity you can imagine. But the Prie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> being come, the King gave the Bride <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Marriage; and after the Solemnity, they were Treated at a moſt Magnificent Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:51812:51"/> but nothing Feaſted them more, than the deligate and charming Behaviour of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ride, which was ſo full of Attracti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll preſent, became Tributary to her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y. The Muſick, all the time, entertained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Ears with an excellent Conſort, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imes of Viols, ſometimes of Voices, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he beſt Songs for that occaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n; until a Meſſenger, from the Gally, acq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainted the Brid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>groom it was time to put to Sea; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich immediately the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did, and going into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he King's Coach, he in Perſon accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d them to the Veſſel, where Embracing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he young <hi>Grecian</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Lady; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing them many rich Preſents, according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Quality, the Nobles a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſo pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat Acknowledgement, they Embarked in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Gally,</hi> and were quickly out of ſight; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut all the while they were in view, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, and his Princes were drinking to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Bon-Voyage on the Strand, often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſcourſing of the extraordinary Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns of the Bridegroom, and the ſurpaſſing Beauty of the Bride. The Ship out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght, the King haſtens to his Tower, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uaint his Queen of the Wonders he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>een that day; and that the <hi>Grecian</hi> Lady <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery much reſembled her, as ſhe had told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im; but being come into the Chamber, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>retched King could ſee nothing but forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:51812:52"/> Walls, and an open Caſement, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which, he might eaſily conjecture which way the Bird was flown: So that looking out at the forlorn Window, a ſudden Gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs ſeized him, that his Senſes failing, he fell over to the Ground, and miſerably Dyed. Think now Mighty <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Learned <hi>Philantropus,</hi> What Credi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is to be given to a Vicious Lacivious Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: And let the excellent Diſcourſes you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have had of this kind, prevail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with You<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Imperial Clemency, to forbear the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sentence againſt the Incomparable <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtus,</hi> until the Matter be fully debated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Senate, leſt, too late, you repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your over Credulity and Raſhneſs. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Emperor thanking the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeaſonable Advice; promiſed to follow it; and diſmiſſed him with a conſiderable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:51812:52"/>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <p>NOw was the Implacable <hi>Aphrodicea</hi> in the greateſt extremity of Rage, and Confuſion; having ſtill been defeated of her Helliſh Purpoſes, and Deſigns on the Perſon of the Incomparable <hi>Eraſtus:</hi> For the High Sheriff of the City, during <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian</hi>'s Retirement, had took occaſion to viſit a Country Houſe, he had ſome Forty Miles from <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that the King's War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant came not to his hand, until the day after; when the Emperor, by the Interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:51812:53"/> of <hi>Philantropus,</hi> had recalled his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, with reſolution to put the whole Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter under the determination of the Senate. This, as we ſaid, was ſo great a diſapoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Diabollical Queen, that ſhe ordared a Train of Coaches, and Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, with a great Retinue, which were in readineſs to have removed her into the Territories of her own Relations; when the Aſtoniſhed Emperor Arriving from his Country Pallace, was much ſurprized at ſo ſtrange an Equipage; and Admiring what it meant, was informed by a Courtier, that had marked the whole proceeding, That the Empreſs was moving her ſelf out of the Dominions of <hi>Diocleſian;</hi> pretending ſhe could not have. Iuſtice, in the ſatisfaction her Honour claimed on <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> for (as ſhe call'd it) his Inhumane and Traiterous At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon her Perſon: Thus many times are the moſt Helliſh Deſigns, and ſuch as would have the moſt ſavage <hi>Sythians</hi> bluſh, Varniſhed with the ſhinning Laere of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Honour. This was now the laſt Card ſhe had to Play; and therefore, with all imaginable Cunning, ſhe acted the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-part of an Innocent Perſon, that lay under the greateſt Injuries, Violences, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities, and Abuſes that Injuſtice it ſelf, or the greateſt Misfortunes could poſſibly
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:51812:53"/> Expoſe her to: Oft would ſhe beat her Breaſt with her hand, and diſcharge ſuch Vollies of Sobs and Sighs, as if her Heart, a Priſoner there, would force its way out of its Irkſom Lodging: So that the Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Diocleſian</hi> finding her on the Ground in this miſerable plight, being naturally Compaſſionate, eſpecially to Objects of this kind, which are certainly the moſt moving, and Heart-wounding Language in the World: The abuſed Emperor lifted her up in his Armes, and mingling his Tears with hers, promiſed the next Morning to put an end to the Cauſe of her Sorrow and Affliction; and therefore gave Order to the Servants to bring in the Trunks that had been laid in the Carriages; and ſpending the Afternoon in drying the Queens Eyes, he gave her opportunity to inſinuate her Treaſons, to that degree, that he believed her the moſt Innocent, and Abuſed of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and himſelf Deſigned upon by the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> who (now he doubted not) had contrived to Depoſe him, and ſet up their Tool <hi>Eraſtus</hi> in his ſtead: 'Tis ſtrange that the Poyſon of one baſe Womans Rage, and Revenge ſhould ſpread ſo far; but no doubt the Devil that ſet her on work, had furniſhed her with Councellers, and Abettors of her Deſigns: Since Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:51812:54"/> Courts have never wanted ſuch, as for Covetouſneſs, or Ambition, would not ſtick at the moſt Execrable Villainies. But leaving them to their laſt Act; hugging themſelves, in hope that their curſed Plot had took Effect; we ſhall now begin to draw our Tragedy to a Concluſion, and ſhew you, by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Example, the admirable, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Care, that Heaven takes of the Innocent; and how certainly, in due time, it detects, and brings to Iuſtice, the moſt Potent, and Politick Contrivers of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:51812:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <p>NOw was the Morning come of that which was deſigned to have been one of the blackeſt, and fouleſt that ever the bright Eye of Heaven had lookt upon: The Guards were ready, the honeſt Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens and Senators in Tears, and great Confuſion, apprehending the fatal Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of that Bloody day: The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, in the greateſt Tranſport of blinded Rage, reſolved (as he thought) to put an end to the Fears that attend Crowned, Hends, eſpecially when they are Impoſed upon, by the Malignant Influences of Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Woman-craft: The Empreſs, and her Ladies dreſt in their greateſt Bravery, her Prieſts kindling the Fire on the Altar, to ſing <hi>Te Deum</hi> at the curſed Stroke: The Innocent Prince Adorned with all the Beauties of ſhining Virtue; and Moral Gallantry, deſpiſing the worſt Potent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and Mallice could Attempt upon him, and with moſt Heroick Magnanimity bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Death it ſelf. All things were thus ready for the moſt Inhumane Act: When the <hi>Philoſopher Lencus</hi> have urged through the Guards, who gave him eaſy paſſage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:51812:55"/> deſirous the Prince might not Fall by ſuggeſtions of Treachery, or Mallice: <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> threw himſelf at the Emperors Feet, and delivered him a Paper, whereon was Written to this Effect;
<q>
                     <l>THe Gods to Morrow by Six o'th' Clock,</l>
                     <l>Will Prince <hi>Eraſtus</hi> Lips unlock;</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Diocleſian</hi> ſhall know,</l>
                     <l>Who is his Friend, and who his Foe:</l>
                     <l>Therefore the Heavens bid thee ſtay,</l>
                     <l>The Sentence of thy Rage this day;</l>
                     <l>Or thy neglect, thy Crown ſhall pay.</l>
                  </q> The Emperor ſtartled at this Oraculous way of Writing, and ſtrangely Raviſhed with the News of his Son's returning to Speech; immediately ſent expreſs Order to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Guard to ſtop the Sentence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till farther Order; and calling for the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> ſaid thus unto him. <hi>Lencus,</hi> the Execution of Iuſtice hath been often preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by you, and your fellows, and it may be out of ſome deſign; but be aſſured, if <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtus</hi> do not ſpeak by to Morrow Six of the Clock, you ſhall All run the ſame Fate with him; to which, the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I receive Your Majeſties Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with all Submiſſion. And although theſe Learned Men that have Attended Your
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:51812:55"/> Imperial Majeſty before me, on the ſame Occaſion, have recited many excellent Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſetting forth the Baſeneſs, and Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a Deceitful Woman, and Confirmed them with divers Tragical Examples, of the Falſeneſs, and Cruelty of that Implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ex: I do, with all Humility, return Your Majeſty thanks for your favourable retracting your Royal Sentence this day, and humbly Crave leave by one Example more, to Evince to Your Highneſs what my Brethren have Inſiſted upon, until to Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhall Convince you, beyond the Power of Suſpicion. Whereupon the Emperor commanding him, he thus proceeded: Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Sir, the Story of the Epheſian Lady is ſo noted, being recited in divers Authors, that I ſhall be much the briefer in my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. She had buried her Husband ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what near the City, according to the cuſtom of that Country, and had built a little Room in the Sepulchre, where ſhe intended (with the greateſt Mortification that was ever heard of) to finiſh the reſt of her Life in the company of that beloved Corps: She had not been long a Recluſe in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant manner, when a Malefactor that had been Executed, was hung not far from this Tomb; the cuſtom of <hi>Epheſus</hi> being to have the Body of the Malefactor watched
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:51812:56"/> by a Souldier for ſome certain days, that it might be expoſed to the greater Terror of others; and if it happened to be ſtolen from the Gibbet, then the Sentinel was to be hung in the room of the Criminal. The Weather being cold, and the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel perceiving a Light not far from him, it being Night, drew towards it; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Door of the Sepulchre, craved entrance: the half Mortified Widow de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding who he was, was Anſwered; I am a Souldier, ſet by Order of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, to Guard the Body of a Malefactor Executed here this Morning, for Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; but the Night being ſo extream cold, I know not why it may not be eſteemed as great Charity in your Ladyſhip, as well to admit the Living into your company, as to afford your company to the Dead. The Woman opened the Door, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Souldier, who might ſoon perceive the Tide of her Sorrows; give way to ſome other Contemplations; ſhe was content to exchange Glances with him, and permitted him to Entertain her with his diſcourſe; which you may imagine to be ſuch, as brisk young Sons of <hi>Mars</hi> entertain handſome Women withal. In ſhort, ſhe began to be weary of her Dead Companion, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, that the Society of a Living one
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:51812:56"/> might be more agreeable; ſhe was prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with to take a dragme of his Bottle, the Air of that place being ſomewhat raw, and damp; ſo that a brisk Gayity began to ſhew in her Face: in this pleaſant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the Red-coat paſſed ſo much time, that returning to his Charge, he found the Body gone indeed; ſo that being half Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, he returned to the diſconſolate Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, deſiring once again to be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that lonely Vault, which was ſoon gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and acquainting her of his ill circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, by reaſon the Corps of the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal had been removed; there might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, in his Countenance, an Aſpect, much more diſmal than what the Widow had put on, when ſhe ſhut up her ſelf with her Dead Husband. The Woman ſeeing him in this ſad dumps, began to entertain ſome Fears, leſt ſhe ſhould loſe her new Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, in the Porch of her Expectations; and having, according to the Faculty of that Sex, a quick Invention in the Nick of Exegent, ſhe began thus to Salve his Sorrows, Souldier (ſaid ſhe) be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid; ſhe that is willing to Exchange a Dead Husband for a Living, need never a better occaſion to accompliſh her deſires: Behold, the Carcaſs of my Dead Husband is at your Devotion, as well as the Body
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:51812:57"/> of his Living Widow, who is now reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to loſe no more of her Iuice in fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly bewailing an unprofitable Cavaver, but to reſerve it for the allaying your A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Heats (my Dear Souldier) ſaid ſhe; and Embracing him, began to Fan away the Sorrows from his Cheeks, take this loathſome Trunk then, and hang it in the room of the Fellon; and glad am I, the old Villain ſerves to ſo good uſe. Dear Madam, replied the Sentinel, the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner will ſoon diſcover the Cheat; for the Body of the Thief wanted a Leg, and an Arm; beſides, his Eares were cropt, and his Genitals cut off; And is it then ſo difficult (ſaid ſhe) to reduce this Corps to the ſame form? And taking his <hi>Cimetar,</hi> ſhe chopt off a Leg, and Arm; and with his Knife, cropt and lopt the Premiſes; giving thereby a moſt ſignal Teſtimony of Female Conſtancy, and Affection: Now, ſaid ſhe, dear Centinel, we have nought to do, but to hang up this Cripple, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain our ſelves with Enjoyments ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Living. I will rather hang up my ſelf, ſaid he, than be Ioyned to a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo Infamous; ſhe that can offer ſuch Violence to the Body of a Dead Husband will be ready to do ſo to the Living, for a freſh Gallant: And ſo haſted out of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:51812:57"/> leaving her to bewail the effect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Cruelty, and diſappointment of her Luſt.</p>
               <p>Can any thing be more frequent in Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, or Obſervation, than the Frands, Gulls, and Shams of inſatiate Women? But I ſhall now give Your Highneſs no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arther trouble, but leave the proof of what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have ſaid, unto to Morrow; repeating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gain my moſt Humble Thanks to Your Majeſty for this days Reverſion of the Princes Sentence; for the which, you will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave cauſe to make the Altars of the Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Smoak.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:51812:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX.</head>
               <p>NOw had the Glorious Morn to this Propitious day, put on her Roſy Mantoa, ſpotted with Gold; and dreſt the Sky in a guilded Tapeſtry, expreſſing the happy Succeſs of that day: She no ſooner peept out at the Eaſtern Windows, but ſhe was Saluted with all the Harmony of the Aiery Quire; which made the Groves, and Vallies Eccho to their ſhrill Muſick; whilſt the purling Streams Danc'd the Hayes, in winding Meanders to the well Tun'd Conſort. Such a beautious Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity might be obſerved, as if Vniverſal Nature had put on her beſt Apparel, and utmoſt Gayity: When the Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> Dres'd in his Native Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and Acquired Excellencies (with unmatch't Luſtre, Out-ſhined the Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the others Glories; and ſeem'd a Diety, for whoſe Entertainment, the other Pomps had been prepared) came Attended with his Guard, and his Faithful Tutors, to the Gate of the Royal Pallace, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Admittance to his Princely Father. What ſhall I ſay! Down fell the Iron Gates; the Guards were Petrified, Eſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:51812:58"/> at the Majeſty of the Preſence, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Charming Oratory of every Accent: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery Eye was Raviſhed, every Heart Tranſported at the All-conquering Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence of ſuch Admir'd Perfection; All ſtruck <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umb with Ioy, at the Opening of his Lips, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd with Exceſs of Affection to his Princely Perſon: A Conquering Sweetneſs ſhewed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n every Geſture; and a Commanding Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y dwelt upon his Lips. Being in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat Hall of the Pallace, the Seven Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters perſwaded him, not ſuddenly to ſhew himſelf to the Emperor, leſt a Violent Exceſs of Ioy ſhould prejudice him: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> that laſt waited upon <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> went to his Dreſſing-Chamber, where the Emperor was making ready to Enquire of Matters; and acquainted him, That the Innocent <hi>Eraſtus</hi> was now come to Compurgate himſelf of the Horrid Crimes, and Treaſons, that Helliſh Mallice had laid to his <hi>Charge:</hi> But deſired, that, before the Enterview, His Imperial Majeſty would prepare himſelf for the Reception of ſo Violent a Ioy, by admitting ſome Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to Vſher that ſurprizing Welcome. The Kings Violius were called in, and one of them ſung a moſt incomparable Song, much like that of Young <hi>Jemmy;</hi> ſome think the Latter to be but a Tranſlation
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:51812:59"/> of it. Then appeared the moſt Abuſed Son and Diſabuſed the moſt deluded Father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when caſting himſelf at the Feet of <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian,</hi> and kiſſing his Royal Knees: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods Great Sir (ſaid he) will not always permit the Innocent to be Vnfortunate— and would have uttered much more, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Over-joy'd Emperor ſtopt his Mouth will a Torrent of Tears, that fell from his Royal Eyes on the Princes Cheeks. But whilſt Father and Son were in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy, all the Emperors Apartment was fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Ioyful Throngs of Honeſt Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and Citizens; which made the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace Ring again with their loud Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This Muſick Awaked <hi>Aphrodicea,</hi> who Enquiring the meaning of that Noiſe, was anſwered by one of her Bed-Chamber, That it was Prince <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> who was now come to Compurgate himſelf to his Father; and was by the Emperor received with the higheſt Carreſſes imaginable: She there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to ſave the Hangman a labour, ſent for her Confeſſor; who having given her Abſolution, &amp; Tallow'd her for a long Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; ſhe dexterouſly cut her own Throat, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Kings Guards were come in to Seize her, in order for her Tryal. This being underſtood by the now convinced <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> ſhe was privately Buryed in <hi>Flora's</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:51812:59"/> all her Courtiers, Secretaries, and great Officers, eſcaping, as well as they could, the Storm Impending. One of her Ladies, that uſed to Lye with the Queen, the Prince would needs have uncloathed in the Royal Preſence, who appearing to be a Man, gave a ſufficient Teſtimony of his Miſtreſſes Morals. Diocleſian asked his Sons Forgiveneſs, for having Diſtruſted, and Abuſed ſuch unparalell'd Innocence; he Crowned him King of the Romans in full Senate, Preferred the Seven Excellent Philoſophers, highly approving their Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Courage, and Fidelity: Ordered ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Oblations to be made, and Sacrifice paid ſo the Supream Iuſtice, that had Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly Saved him a Son, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire a Prince; and one of ſuch Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, as the World could not ſhew his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell. Many days were ſpent in the City, and Country, in publick Triumphs, and Magnificencies; and to this day there is, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ught to be, an Aniverſary obſerved in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the Incomparable Eraſtus.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="supplement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51812:60"/>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:51812:60"/>
            <head>A Supplement To the LIFE of <hi>Prince Eraſtus.</hi> By the ſame Hand.</head>
            <p>HItherto we have Related the great Misfortunes (if we may ſo call the Tryal of Heroick Virtue) that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the excellent <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> and it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable to Conſider, with what Impudence, the moſt bloody Mallice, and damn'd Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, dare Magnify themſelves in the Courts of the greateſt Monarchs; What, Mighty Patrons the groſſeſt Injuſtice, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Conſpiracies ſhall meet withal! One
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:51812:61"/> would have thought it impoſſible for all the Fiends of Hell, to have laid ſuch a Train of Miſchief againſt the Innocent, as this Helliſh Woman had contrived againſt this unparalell'd Prince? To have Chaſtity branded with Incontinence; nay a Rape, the moſt Loyal Son, and Subject; repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Rebel, and Vndutiful. The Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant proclaimed a Coward; and that Prince, whoſe incomparable Gallantry had ſignalized him to the whole World, to be Rediculed, Traduced, and impudently Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed? Is this the Fate of the Generous, and Heroick; the Virtuous, and the Brave? Or is it ſo dangerous for Princes to keep themſelves unſullied from the Taint of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, and the modiſh Vices of the Court? But it's now high time to turn the Scale, and acquaint you with the Glorious Sun-ſhine that ſucceeded this Storm, and the happy Serenity that enſued upon this Tempeſtuous Morning. The Ioy of the Tranſported <hi>Romans</hi> had now over-ſlown the Banks of their own <hi>Tyber,</hi> and ſent the happy News of <hi>Eraſtus</hi>'s Deliverance into the remoter Parts of the Empire: So that all the depending Princes ſent their great Embaſſadors to Congratulate, and Compliment on ſo Extraordinary an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. Nor were the Triumphs, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:51812:61"/> demonſtrations of Ioy, confined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Walls of <hi>Rome;</hi> but had diffuſed and ſpread themſelves over the Face of all the Provinces: So that, by the many Bonfires (which in the Night Inlightend the Air, as if they deſigned, by Art, to lengthen out the happy day, beyond its natural Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) you would have thought they had Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifized whole Cites for the good Fortune of their Prince. Nothing was omitted that might teſtify the Vniverſal Satisfaction, they received in his ſo wonderful Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. In the midſt of theſe Tranſports, and general Acclamations, the good <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian</hi> (Surfeited with an Extaſy of Ioy) makes a journey to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and reſigns the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire to his Countrys Royal Patron, <hi>Eraſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Rites of the Old Emperor's Funeral were performed (which were done with a Pomp ſuitable to the Grandure of his High Dignity) there appeared another Scene of Triumph; for now came the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation of the Darling of his Country, the Incomparable <hi>Eraſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Senate (who had ever born a juſt Reſpect to the Character, and Vertues of the Heroick <hi>Eraſtus</hi>) now thought they had a ſufficient Opportunity, both to ſignalize their Loyalty to their Prince, and Inveſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:51812:62"/> themſelves in the Affections of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> by ſetting the Imperial Diadem on the Head of the moſt deſerving of Princes: One, whoſe Valour, Patience, Allegiance, and Firmneſs to the Intereſt of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, had ſufficiently Intituled him to the Monarchy of their Hearts.</p>
            <p>All things were now ſet in order to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the Magnificence of that Glorious day; Triumphal Arches were Erected, where, in excellent Figures, were repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, the ſeveral Studies, and Exerciſes the Prince had been Trained up in his Minority: Some were Logical, ſome Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical, ſome Geographical; ſome ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his admirable Horſe-manſhip, and his excellent Dexterity in the uſe of the Sword and Spear; wherein Fame proclaimed him to Excel any Prince Alive in his time. But above all, near the Pallace of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, they had ordered a Coloſſus to be ſet up, whereon, in large Figures, were Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the manner of the Queens Scratching her ſelf, when ſhe pretended, the Prince would have Raviſh't her; his ſevere Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, the cruel Manner that he oft was brought in to the place of Execution; with all the other particulars of the fore-going Hiſtory, admirably Exemplified; which would ſwell this Paper too large to be here
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:51812:62"/> recited: On the top of this, was the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical manner of the Empereſs's violent Death, with the Execution of her Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Prieſts, that had conſented with, and adviſed her to, the bloody Deſign againſt the Life of the Prince: All the Balconies, in the Capitol Streets, were hung with richeſt Tapeſtry, and <hi>Perſian</hi> Silks; they were lined with Beautiful Ladies, and Perſons of great Honour; who ſtill, as the Prince paſſed by, Teſtified their high Approbation of that days Tranſaction. The Senators Guards (all in New Equipage) were placed round the Capitol; (which in <hi>Rome</hi> was the Pallace where the Senate met) and within (on a low Aſſent of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ony inlaid with Gold) was ſet a Chair of State. Around it were Galleries curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Guilded, and filled with more ſhining Beauties; in the midſt, were Couches of Embroidered Velvet, whereon the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſate, richly clad in Scarlet Robes; and having Seated <hi>Eraſtus</hi> in his Chair; the Conſul, or principal Man of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, ſpake to him after this Manner.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>My Lord</hi> Eraſtus,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe People of <hi>Rome</hi> (whoſe Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives we are) have this day unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly Determined to ſet their Imperial
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:51812:63"/> Crown on Your Royal Head; This they do out of the great Confidence they have in Your Princely Virtues, and High Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments for ſo great a Truſt. We have ſeen with what Conſtancy, and Serenity, you have Supported under the greateſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes; and with what Evenneſs of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per you have Graced all Conditions: So that your Noble Qualifications; have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made you Emperor of their Hearts. We therefore require you to Promiſe to keep inviolate the Liberties, and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Roman People; and to uſe that Sword which they put in your Hand, for their Juſt Preſervation and Defence.</p>
                  <p>Then the Prince Ariſing, and lifting up his Hand, Swore by the Gods which they Worſhipped, To maintain the ſame Law among them, as had been Confirmed by the Senate; and to do nothing againſt, but for the Good and Weal of his People.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Vpon this, the Conſul (in the name of the People of <hi>Rome</hi>) ſet the Imperial Crown upon his Head; then with an Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Shout, they proclaimed him Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; which was preſently anſwered by the Guards without, with large Vollies, and Acclamations, and all the Ordinance round the City diſcharged their Thunder. Then
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:51812:63"/> (after a ſplendid Guard of Partizans) the Senators, in order, march to the Pallace-Royal, the Conſul bearing the Sword be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Emperor; who was followed by many Princes of that Empire: Some, of whom, carried an Vmbrel of Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Value over his Head.</p>
            <p>By the way, they were met by the Prieſt, in his formallities; who had ever a wet Mouth to be dealing in Feſtivals; he was going to the Temple, to ſmoak his Gods, on this great Occaſion; and (that he might obtain a Grace at Court) to Offer ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to the Genius of his new Prince, and Lord <hi>Eraſtus.</hi> At the Entry of the Pallace, they were Entertained with a Levit of Five Hundred Trumpets, and in the firſt Court, with all other ſorts of Wind Muſick, in the ſecond Court, with Violins and ſtringed Inſtruments, in the great Hall, with the Organ, Skilfully play'd on; to which, accorded an excellent Voice, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Song.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="song">
                        <head>SONG.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>COme from the Dungeon to the Throne,</l>
                           <l>So much the Gods thy Virtues own:</l>
                           <l>Then Reign, till ſuch as did deſign</l>
                           <l>Thy Ruine; pay for't at the time:</l>
                           <l>For there their Treaſons muſt reſign.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <pb n="120" facs="tcp:51812:64"/>
                           <l>But they are gone! Their Murtherous hands,</l>
                           <l>Prevent the Magiſtrates Commands;</l>
                           <l>They Strangled lye in their own Bands:</l>
                           <l>Whilſt Conquering <hi>Rome</hi>'s proud Diadem,</l>
                           <l>Thy Sacred Temples round doth Hem.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>He that can Teach himſelf t'Obey,</l>
                           <l>Is fit'ſt th' Imperial Sword to Sway;</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Eraſtus</hi> gave his Paſſions Law;</l>
                           <l>And this the Equal Gods then ſaw,</l>
                           <l>And Sav'd him, Mighty Realms to Aw.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This ended, they withdrew into the more private Rooms, and were there Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd with as much Gallantry, as the Pomp of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to. The reſt of the Night was paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Magnificent Maſques and Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, which wonderfully expreſſed many Hiſtorical, and curious Figures. Some few days more were ſpent in Courtly Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantries, and Royal Entertainments; whilſt the City Conduits flowed with Wine, and all Imaginable Expreſſions of a Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Ioy, range in every corner of the Streets. It was wonderful to ſee what a Mighty Change there was in the Face of things, in the City of <hi>Rome:</hi> For the Senators, and principal Citizens, who, but few days ſince, were in great heavineſs;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:51812:64"/> and entering into Mourning for the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous Cruelty to be Executed on their moſt Accompliſht Prince; were now filled with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayity, and Satisfaction at the happineſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey enjoyed, in having him preſerved; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er whoſe Government they could not doubt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all the bleſſings that attend the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ration of a Prudent Monarch. Even now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou could have heard nothing but Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tions, and ſad Camplaints of <hi>Diocleſians</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnatural Cruelty to his Excellent Son; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he whole City ſeeming to languiſh in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niverſal ſadneſs: But now, Smiles and Triumphs ſate on every face, and the Air <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>choed with Shoutings, Acclamations, Mirth and Muſick.</p>
            <p>Strange, but very pleaſant was the Change, the Prince (with good reaſon) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leved himſelf the greateſt Potentate on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee of the Earth, becauſe he ruled in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery Souls of his Subjects: (<q>For even in the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> we find, That a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannick, all Controuling, ſway a rough and Auſtere Management, made the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Odious and Vnſupportable, when on the other hand Moderation and Clemency, a Compliance with the Senate, and a Tenderneſs of the Publick Good; hath ſo far recommended the Prince, that it hath Extended his Empire, and made it more
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:51812:65"/> Abſolute and Terrible to his Enemies, than all the Severe and Arbitrary Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods in the World could e're pretend to.</q>) So that nothing in the World hath ſo much promoted the Grandure of the Monarch, as this Popular and Gentle way.</p>
            <p>Yet ſome there were who Secretly murmured at this Tranquillity, whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed Eyes could not bear the Splendor of this glorious and equal Government, theſe (being Enemyes to Mankind, and of the Nature of the Devil) repined a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whatſoever promoted the peace and welfare of the Publick; indeed nothing in the World ſo grated their Spirits, and ſet their blood in a kind of Ferment, as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good. They were perfect haters of Morality, and could not endure the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of any thing that but lookt like Virtue; Maſſacres and Stakes, Rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Axes, Iayls, and Gibbets were the brave proſpects that delighted them: like <hi>Nero</hi> they could ſing Carols at the Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing City. Nothing in nature was ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to them, as a Calm and ſerene Seaſon. They delight in Stormes and Hurricanes; for like Sharkes and Whales they thrive by Tempeſts, and Live upon the Publick Wrack. But theſe Envipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated wormes, were now crept into their
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:51812:65"/> holes, and there ſecretly Croak't out their Venom, for they were not able to ſtand before the Iuſtice of the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate.</p>
            <p>Theſe were ſome of the principal ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tes of the late wicked Empreſs, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly fit Tools of her Prieſts to work with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l; Nothing ſo fit to promote Vitious and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe Deſignes, as Perſons of Immortal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Debaucht Principles: Therefore that theſe wicked Prieſts, might not want fit Inſtruments to carry on their bloody De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, they firſt poiſoned their Proſelites with all manner of Corrupt, and Noiſom Theorems, which their Vitiated Natures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are too apt to Imbibe: that ſo (having ſufficiently Renounced whatſoever lookt like Moral) they might be the better qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ified for the Villanies they were to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etrats. Theſe were they (who having by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe wayes crept into the Court) were ſtill Inſtilling, and buzzing into the Emperours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rs, againſt the moſt Innocent and Duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince <hi>Eraſtus:</hi> For from the time the Queen had made her firſt complaint, they ceaſed not to aggravate whatſoever ſhe ſuggeſted againſt him; alwayes Inſinuating their whiſpers in detraction of his Virtue, and ſhamming over all his Excellent Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments, with falſe Callumnies, and ſlanderous Imputations; never permitting
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:51812:66"/> the abuſed <hi>Diocleſian</hi> to view his Son, but through their falſe perſpectives, that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him all over Monſter. By theſe Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Artifices, the deluded Emperour had been trapanned to Ruine both himſelf and the Empire, had not the Iuſtice of the Gods raiſed up the <hi>Seven Wiſe Maſters,</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, to prevent the Fatal Blow.</p>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. The War of the Emperour <hi>Eraſtus</hi> with King <hi>Siwel,</hi> the manner of his Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</head>
               <p>NOw tho theſe Infernal Agents found all their baſe Attempts Succeſſeſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Incomparable <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> yet could they not ſo ſoon forſake their dear Miſchief, nor be drawn from the ſweet Treaſons they had been ingaged in: but perſiſted ſtill in new Conſults to deſtroy the Young Emperour, and in him the happineſs of the Empire.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Eraſtus</hi> (whoſe noble Soul taſted no reliſh in all the Splendid Feaſts, Masks, and Effeminate Entertainments of the Court) Imagining that he that wore an
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:51812:66"/> Imperial Crown, was by the Gods deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſomewhat elſe beſides ſoft Luxury; and that buſineſs of greater Importance was appointed for him that ſat at the Helm of Empire; thereby manifeſting the Conduct of a Wiſe and Gallant Prince. Appointed the Senate to meet at the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol in three Dayes, and all things being in Readineſs for that great Aſſembly, the day of their Congreſs being come, they firſt met in the Forum, and the Emperour, with a Royal Retinue being come to them, they there put on their Reſpective Robes, and in great State proceeded to the Imperial Chamber, the Roof whereof was raiſed on Pillars of fine Porphirie, curiouſly wrought with Chapiters of Gold: The Ceiling was of Antick Work, wherein were Carved the many Victories of their Famous Generals, with Figures aptly repreſenting the ſeveral Provinces; A Sumptuous Figure ſhewed it ſelf in a ſtately Oval in the Midſt, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the <hi>Roman</hi> State, to which the other Provinces, ſeemed to ſtretch their hands, humbly Supplicating her protection; at one end was ſet a Royal State for the Emperour, whereon he Seated himſelf, and the Senators being ſet on Chairs covered with Tiſſue; the Noble Emperour made them an excellent Oration, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:51812:67"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>
                                 <hi>Moſt Renowned</hi> Romans,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>BY Your Kindneſs, and for your ſakes i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> is, that I wear this Diadem; the Care therefore that reſults from the Truſt You have laid on me, hath occaſioned my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing You together; for I cannot be one of thoſe that think it ſufficient if they get the Reignes of Government into their hand, and then take no farther care what becomes of the Common-Wealth. <hi>My Lords,</hi> I know their are great Duties incumbant on a Crowned Head, and the burthen will be too heavy for me, unleſs Aſſiſted by Your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels; You are the moſt proper Adviſers I can poſſibly Conſult with, for I think the Intereſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> of the Prince, and his People Inſeparably Interwoven: Let us therefore Joyntly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to promote the Publick good, and preſerve the Peace of the Empire: Our Neighbour <hi>Siwel</hi> (who lately was Our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and held his Crown of the <hi>Romans</hi>) is of late grown formidable in Armes, and a great diſturber of the Tranquility of his Quiet Neighbours; Invading their Terito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Depopulating their Countryes with Intollerable outrage. It is not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Grandure, or Pollicy of the <hi>Roman</hi> State to permit ſuch Inſolences. We are farther Informed, that by his Maſqued
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:51812:67"/> Emiſaries, he keeps alive, and foments a Party amongſt thoſe Miſcreants, who were the Creatures of the Late miſerable Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs: Let us therefore Unite our Councels, Aſume our Courage, and Scourge the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable Preſumption of this Proud Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor; let us diſcord his Factors here, and Oppoſe his Forces in the Neighbour Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces; that it may not be ſaid Hereafter, The <hi>ROMAN STATE</hi> was loſt, when <hi>ERAST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> ſat at the Helm.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This Incomparable Speech of the brave Young Emperor, was received by the Senate is an Oracle; their loud Acclamations teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng the high Approbation they had of their Prince, and the Noble Advice he gave them. They verily thought all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> happy conſtellations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f their Great Anceſtors, had clubd together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> confer the Noble Genius of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Heroes on Eraſtus, with ſuch profound VViſdom did he ſearch into the Affaires of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he State, with ſuch brave Gallantry, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olve to oppoſe the Power of Prince Siwel, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd with ſuch Affection Eſpouſe the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt of his Country; that the Antienteſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Senate ſeemed as amazed at the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtick Sweetneſs of his Incomparable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, and charming Oratory.</p>
               <p>Several of the Senators ſtrained their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hetorick in Congratulating the happy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne of the Empire, that had in the Throne
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:51812:68"/> a Prince of ſuch Excellencies, and ſublime Endowments, as from whom they could not hope for any good, but what they might reap by his courage, nor fear any ill; but what would be prevented by his Wiſdom. At length the Conſul recapitulated, and enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, the ſeveral Paragraphs of Eraſtus his Speech; and Moved that they might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, put the Matters therein contained upon the Debate. But it was ſoon deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the Affirmative, there being not one Rotten Member in that well Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Body, that offered to oppoſe the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt of the State. They therefore reſolved to take as many as they could, of their ſecret Enemies into cuſtody, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to raiſe an Army to march into Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, there to oppoſe the Forces of the Revolted Siwel: Eraſtus himſelf offering to March in the head of the Army. Imediate Orders were diſpatched to the Keeper of the Magazines, that they ſhould provide all ſorts of Armes, and Amunition for the Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Several other decrees paſt, for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick matters; which will not fall under the cognizance of this Hiſtory: We ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore continue the Relation of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments between Eraſtus the Emperor; and Siwel King of the Gauls.</p>
               <p>Scarce had the Drums given the ſignal in the Street of the City, that the Senate had determined to enter into a War with the Gauls, and reduce them to their forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Obedience to the Roman State, but the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:51812:68"/> Forum was thronged with Multitudes from all parts of the City, ſo that in two dayes they had Liſted an Army of Forty Thouſand; which was thought ſufficient (they ſtill retaining the Tryed Valour of the Noble <hi>Romans</hi>) to oppoſe a far greater Number of the <hi>Gauls.</hi> Nor were they confined for want of <hi>Volunteers</hi> to ſo ſmall an Army; for the People offered themſelves ſo readily to promote this War, as if they had entertained a Vniverſal hatred to that perfidious Nation. Long had this Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous King <hi>Siwel,</hi> by under-hand Practiſes ſought to undermine, and by open Violence oppoſed (at ſeveral times) the <hi>Roman</hi> Power; and in his Province, with great cruelty deſtroyed many Townes and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies which he thought had Friendſhip for the <hi>Roman</hi> State: So that <hi>Eraſtus</hi> had but two juſt cauſe to chaſtiſe him for his breach of Faith, and evil practiſes. Therefore in few dayes the Army Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the confines of <hi>Gaul,</hi> and by the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deinneſs of their March had entered ſome Leagues into the Country of <hi>Siwel,</hi> before he had time to draw his Forces together to oppoſe them: The Townes and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages in their March, Ioyfully putting themſelves under the protection of <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> being no longer able to hear the Tyrany of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:51812:69"/> their Savage Maſter. <hi>Eraſtus</hi> ſent for more Fortes to the Senate, which he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Gariſons to defend the Country from the Cruelty of <hi>Siwel,</hi> and his Forces; and being come in a dayes March of the <hi>Galick</hi> Army, he entred into a large Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane Country, fit for his deſigned Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; where he poſted himſelf, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched his Camp, the better to obſerve the Motion of the Enemy. The <hi>Gauls</hi> were now approached within a Mile of the Imperial Troops, and having diſcovered that <hi>Eraſtus</hi> his Force Conſiſted but of Forty Thouſand (his own Army being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Hundred Thouſand) he reſolved (according to his wonted Valour) to give them Battle the next Morning; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly having given notice to his ſeveral Quarters, they appeared very early on the Plain, in half a Mile of <hi>Eraſtus</hi>'s Camp: His Scouts, in the mean time, had given him notice of the Enemies motion; ſo that his Army was in as great forwardneſs to Advance, as the <hi>Gauls</hi> were to receive him; Therefore drawing his Men out of the Camp, he Poſted on a convenient ſide of the Plain, in a little more than a Flight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot of <hi>Siwels</hi> Army; with undaunted Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very faceing a Foe of almoſt Treble his Number. In the mean time the <hi>Gauls</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:51812:69"/> had diſcovered, that <hi>Roman</hi> Baggage was left in the Trenches, and guarded but by a few Bow-men, and ſome light Horſe with Lanches: At this <hi>Siwel</hi> (being ever more inclined to plunder than to fight) Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Left Wing, to fall down, and make themſelves Maſters of the Imperial Carriages. The Emperor (though he ſoon perceived the deſign) gave them opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Advance within Shot of the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which were maintained with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Courage, by that very ſmall Guard; not an Arrow they diſcharged, but did its Execution; the Lawnce-men with notable Reſolution keeping the Horſe from enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſmall breach, their Pioneers had made; inſomuch that they diſmounted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Gauls</hi> from their Horſe, who were never able to mount again. Now they were thus far engaged, <hi>Eraſtus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a ſingle Brigade of his Right Wing, to relieve the Waggons; ſo that ſpeedily falling on the Rear of the <hi>Gallick</hi> Right Wing, they did ſuch Execution, that in little time, almoſt half of them were ſlain, or wounded, or taken Priſoners; the reſt with great Confuſion falling into the Body of their Army. This defeat ſo Exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Siwel,</hi> ſeeing ſo great a Body of his Men routed by a handful, that he preſent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:51812:70"/> came on with the main Body of his Army, thinking to cruſh the ſmall Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade of <hi>Eraſtus</hi> his Troops to Pieces; but he little Conſidered the ſteady Vallour of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who never thought that worth the name a Victory, that had not been obtained at ſome great diſadvantage; that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had long before known what it was to Conquer the <hi>Gauls;</hi> and therefore were leſs apt to be daunted by their Noiſe or Numbers.</p>
               <p>The Emperor (diſcovering that he had no ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kill in Martial Diſcipline, or Stratagems of War) had choſen out a Bris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que Forlorn of about three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred tryed Souldiers; theſe were all coat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Male, after the <hi>Roman</hi> manner, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Scythian Spears,</hi> and <hi>Symiters</hi> of <hi>Ruſſian Steel,</hi> their Horſes too had Armor of <hi>Proof;</hi> theſe he ordered to brake through the Ranks of <hi>Siwels</hi> Army, which they did with ſuch force, that their courage levell'd whole Files before them; doing ſuch wonders, that ſhould they be here related, it might be lookt on as a <hi>Romance.</hi> The Violence of their Action, ſoon put the <hi>Gallick</hi> Army in diſorder (for they indeed, were more uſed to purchaſe a Victory with their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, than their Valour; having rarely met with an Enemy that had Courage like the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:51812:70"/> 
                  <hi>Romans;</hi>) ſo that <hi>Eraſtus</hi> coming up to them with the ſmall Body of his Army, ſoon made himſelf Maſter of the Field: Whilſt <hi>Siwel</hi>'s Right Wing (ſeeing the Fate of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he reſt) never ſtood an Engagement, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed the Field: But being cloſely purſued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the Left Wing of the <hi>Romans,</hi> there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere but few of them eſcaped, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y home the News of their Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrow. <hi>Eraſtus</hi> (ſtill) where he thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here was any one Maſter of more than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommon Courage; pickt that perſon out for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Rival, and by that means gave ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al of them the Honor to fall by his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and: but this he did, hoping to ſend the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nemy of his Country, and the principal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccaſion of this m ſchief, to waſh his Crimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Stygian Lake; But <hi>Siwel</hi> had no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch deſign, (for doubting his Fate too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe purſued him) he (with one or two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f his Councel) ſought to flye the Field; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut falling into the hands of a Party of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Romans,</hi> was by them brought Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er to <hi>Eraſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was juſt then retired to his Tent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iving orders for the diſpoſal of the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers; and the better refreſhing his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers after that Dayes Signalizing their Valours. <hi>Siwel</hi> at his approach to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eror (diſcovering a mean and degenerous
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:51812:71"/> Soul, which uſually creeps, and fawns when unfortunate) caſt himſelf at the Feet of the Brave Eraſtus; and with Vn-Princely Cowardize, begged for his wretched Life, and that with ſuch miſerable Submiſſion, as largely teſtifyed the Narrowneſs of his Soul; But this beggarly Action of his, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inflamed, than abated the Iuſt Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Roman Emperor; ſo that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Treating him with that reſpect that a manly Bravery alwayes claims of a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Enemy, he orderd him to be bound in Chains; and in that poſture he followed the Emperors Chariot in his Marches through the Country. So much had the Tyrany and Cruelty of this unworthy Prince Exaſperated the minds of his own Subjects againſt him; that ſtill as he paſſed, they denyed him the common Teſtimonyes of Pitty due to the Miſerable; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached him with his Breach of Faith and Inhumane Oppreſſions, whereby he had En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved, and reduced his Own Province to a State of Beggary and Vaſſallage. In the mean time with loudeſt Acclamations they Applauded the Conduct, Gallantry and good Fortune of Eraſtus; Thanking the God of Victory, that by his hand had redeemed them from the Intollerable Bondage they endured under the cruel Tyrany of the baſe minded Siwel. So natural is it to Mankind to hate a Tyrant, and give all poſſible demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of their Satisfaction, and enlarged Ioy, under the Sweet Influences of an
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:51812:71"/> equal Adminiſtration. The Generous-Soul'd Eraſtus, (ſtill as he paſſed hrough the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages and Citties of that Country) with a Princely greatneſs confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>med to them thoſe Priviledges, which Siwel's Injuſtice had robbed them of, and beſtowed on them ſuch other Teſtimonies of his Royal Favours, as beſpoke him to be a Prince hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning the Weal, and happineſs of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and not the rugged Satisfaction of a Tyranical or Ambitious Monarch. He Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred them to chooſe Governours of their own, to ſee Iuſtice duely Adminiſtred, and the Peoples Righ s kept Inviolate: Who were to be Reſponſible to the Imperial Chamber for their neglects therein</p>
               <p>Thus in a very ſhort time were the Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growing Evils of thoſe Provinces rooted up; and (by the great care of that Excellent Emperor) the pleaſant Plants of Publick Tranquility and a general Peace grew up in the room of them. Here was confuſion reduced into Order, Riotous Debauchery, reformed to manly Sobriety, and a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Morality, Tyranny and Oppreſſion were Banniſhed, and Equity, and Clemency took place? The Groans and Tears of the Oppreſſed Gauls were turned into Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs; and Every man had his Life, and Labor, once more called his Own. Having thus happyly ſetled Affairs in thoſe Parts, the Emperour returned in great. Tryumph to Rome: and was there received by the Senate and Citizens with ſuch a welcom,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:51812:72"/> as well ſhewed the ſence they had of their Happyneſs under his Auguſt, and propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Influence.</p>
               <p>I might here relate the Magnificence of his ſplendid Reception, by giving the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the particulars of the Trophies, Arches, Companies, Pageants: and all the brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes which Poets uſually feign, to guild their <hi>Romances;</hi> (for indeed the World never ſaw greater Pomps, than thoſe with which the Gallant <hi>Romans</hi> uſed to welcom home their Victorious Generals): But (my deſigne being rather to Paint an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Prince, than a Gaudy Pageant) I ſhall omit the Mention of thoſe leſſer matters: only acquaint the Reader (who may be deſirous to know) what became of the unlucky <hi>Siwel.</hi> He therefore was led to <hi>Rome</hi> in the manner you have heard; and after a few dayes, was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Senate; where the Conſul large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſum'd up the Foulneſs of his Deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Life, telling him, <hi>That he had fallen ſo far below a Prince, that he came ſhort of the very Brutes, which (ordainarily) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to Cheriſh one another; and (in their way) revenge the injuries offered to their kind: but that he (contrary to the very dictates of Brutal Nature) had not only uſurped unto himſelf the Government of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:51812:72"/> but had with great Cruelty, and Rapine, endeavoured to ſupport his Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and unjuſt Uſurpation: So that he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot only Invaded, but even diveſted the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their Natural Rights; refuſing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow them the Common Priviledges, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re the undoubted Claim of Humane Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ures; but that on the Contrary he had exacted of them Tributes larger than their Eſtates could reach unto, and had after a Tyranical manner Levied them by the Power of his Sword; ſetting Ruffenly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cers to Oppreſs the People at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and had refuſed them their Juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, by an application to the Senate; That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e had Treacherouſly withdrawn himſelf from his Obedience to the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, to whom <hi>Gaul</hi> own'd as much Obedience, as the reſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Conqueſts. Adding, that now the Gods had Chaſtiſed him for his Impieties; they left his Treaſons to be Puniſhed as the Victorious <hi>Eraſtus</hi> ſhould direct.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Siwel,</hi> like a Wretch in great dejection (all this time) ſwam in abundance of Tears; and made ſuch pittiful demonſtration, of a Poor, Low and Contemptible Spirit, that it might indeed have moved pitty; had it not proceeded rather from the diſapoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his baſe deſignes; than a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:51812:73"/> of the foulneſs of his Loathſom Crimes. The Generous <hi>Eraſtus</hi> ſcorned to Foul the Sword of the Publick Iuſtice with the Blood of ſuch a Cowardly, and Capon-hearted Miſcreant; but having ſufficiently tyed him up from attempting (any farther) his baſe deſignes; he left him to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Virtues of his paſt Life: The Tranquillity of his Government, and the Diſappointment his Cowardly Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had met withal; which reflections ſoon made ſuch a Battery on his frailty, that his narrow Soul (not longer able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſuch Aſſaults) made its eſcape to his Old Confederate <hi>Pluto,</hi> Prince of the Lower Regions; where doubtleſs he had an Entertainment Suitable to the Deſignes he had managed, and the Service he done on this ſide <hi>Acheron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus he (whoſe Ambition graſpt at Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, whoſe Soul delighted in Cruelty, that had diverted himſelf in Torturing of Others) Expired Vnpittyed, Vnlamented, and left a perpetual Infamy entailed to his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:51812:73"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AFter the Reduction of <hi>Gaul;</hi> whereby it was again made a part of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, ſo univerſal a Serenity Shined in all parts, as if the Gods deſigned under the reign of this Prince to give the world a taſt of that happineſs men enjoy, under a prudent and well-dispoſed Magiſtrate; no Complaints troubled the quiet Pallace, nor did the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour lord it amongſt the humble Cottages. The Shepheard rejoyced in the fruits of his Flock, and the Labourer of his Vines: The Baſhful Virgin knew not what it was to be aſſaulted by the Luſtful violence of the rude Debauches: nor were the Gods denyed their Inſence, though in pots of Clay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nothing was heard over the well-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd Empire, but the voice of a well-tun'd Harmony, and mutual Congratulations for ſo happy a Reſtitution of the common Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility. The Prince ſo Vertuous, no tongue durſt detract him; nor was the Venom of the Quill (at that time) diffuſed, to poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Publique Quiet: Men enjoyed their Eſtates, free from the Envy of the greedy Miſers, and their Religion, without the Flagitious Remarques of Peſtilent Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; or the baſe Reflections of Scandalous
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:51812:74"/> Libellers. The Government was made eaſie to the People; and the Emperour Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the Bleſſings ariſing from ſo well turned a Government. What ſhall I ſay? the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire (till then) never ſaw ſo great ſerenity; nor did the Grandure of any of their Emperours, compare with the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralleled Greatneſs of the moſt Incomparable <hi>Eraſtus.</hi> His admirable Conduct, and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful Adminiſtration, was the Theam of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prudent mans diſcourſe, and of the Poet's Song; the Rival Paſtorals reſounded with the Praiſe of <hi>Eraſtus:</hi> and the unmoleſted Merchant Tranſported his Fame into the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Empire being thus ſetled, to the general ſatisfaction of all good men, the Emperor Reſolved to viſit the Remoter Collonies, and (with his preſence) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liven and cheriſh the hearts of thoſe his Subjects, that had only taſted the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his diſtant Influence; carr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing with his Perſon, all thoſe welcom Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, that uſe to accompany a Prince in favour with the Gods. Purſuant to this his reſolution, he called the Senate (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to do nothing without the Advice of his beſt Council) and communicated to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:51812:74"/> them his Intention; withal committing the care of the Government to their Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, until his return: and giving ſuch other Orders as were neceſſary to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in his Abſence. He took but few of his own Servants with him, and ſome particular Noble Men, that had been ſtill Conſtant to him, during the Frowns of <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> which (with a ſmall retinue) made about an Hundred Horſe. He need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no Guards, for his Intereſt was ſo great in the affections of his People; that he had a Cittadel in every Village, and a Fort in every Breaſt; in fine, all his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories were ſafe as his own Palace: So great is the Influence that a good Prince hath, over the moſt ſordid Diſpoſitions; The moſt Churliſh Boor paid an Homage to his Virtue, and the moſt depraved Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bean was ſtruck with aſtoniſhment, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by his Gallantry.</p>
               <p>His Firſt Progreſs, (after having paſt the Confines of <hi>Italy</hi>) was through the (once Famous) Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the pleaſant Banks of the Fertile Banow; and ſo paſſing through that Gallant Country, ſince fallen to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> be came to the Princely Country of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia;</hi> at that time one of the moſt Flouriſhing
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:51812:75"/> Kingdoms in the World. Through the vaſt number of its Inhabitants, every Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage ſwoll to a City, whoſe lofty Towers and Pallaces, ſhewed a ſtately Proſpect to the Neighbouring Plaines. And though the Great <hi>Eraſtus</hi> met with all the Loyal Careſſes Imaginable, in the whole courſe of his Progreſs; and was received by his People, rather as a God, than one of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Race: Yet could not all theſe Pomps of State, nor the Extraordinaryes of the Entertainments provided for him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw him from the Exerciſe of his Moral Contemplations; or thoſe more Virtuous Conſiderations, which are the Natural pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of a Noble Soul. So that in the midſt of all theſe ſplendid Gayityes, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templative receſs ſeemed more E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igible to the good Emperor: He therefore retired for ſome dayes to a Country Pallace not far from the Stately City of <hi>Prague,</hi> leaving moſt of his Retinue at that Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſtus</hi> was extreamly pleaſed with the ſweet ſolitarineſs of this Caſtle; it had been an Ancient Manſion of the Emperors; and wanted not ſufficient Bravery to teſtify great the quality of its Inhabitant: the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were Lofty, and of Marble: The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partments were ſpatious, and delightful, it ſtood on a ſmall Aſſent of a Hill, which
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:51812:75"/> overlookt a large Valley of many Miles extent, which was repleniſhed with Paſtures, and Vineyards in great abundance; through the midſt of which the Silver-breaſted Danow brought the Treaſures, and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of Foreign Parts, into the heart of that large Country, and Exported their own Wines in Exchange: In ſhort; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was wanting that might recommend the Cituation of this Houſe, for one of the Nobleſt Retraits in the Empire: Only the lonely humour of the Lord, affected not the Noiſe and Tumult of a Numerous and Vnneceſſary Attendance, which was ſo much the more agreeable to the Temper of <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> who had given ſtrict Orders (for his greater privacy) that it ſhould be ſtill reported he continued at the Court at <hi>Prague;</hi> to prevent the Croud that otherwiſe would have ſpoiled his more retired Divertiſements. The Lord of this Pallace dayly Entertained the Emperor with ſuch Airy, and wholſom Sports, of Hunting the <hi>Stagg,</hi> the <hi>Bore,</hi> ſometimes the <hi>Fox,</hi> and other Savages as the Woods and Foreſt could afford; where the Thundring Northern <hi>Hound,</hi> and the Shril-Mouth'd <hi>Beagle,</hi> rang many a Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious peal through the Ecchoing Vallyes: with ſuch kind of Recreations they uſually paſſed the time till Dinner, but the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:51812:76"/> was ſpent in a more ſilent Retirement; for towards the Evening, the Fragrance of the Air, and the Charming Melody of the Airy Quire, commonly called them (through a ſpacious Garden) into an adjoyning Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of Ieſſamines, Mirtles and Roſes; The native Sweetneſs, and Pleaſantneſs of thoſe Walks, drew the Emperor at a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſtance from the Pallace than he was aware of; and brought him at length by the Side of a Chriſtal River, whoſe pretty mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur ſeemed to bear a Conſort with the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therd Choriſters of the adjoyning Grove. On the Bank of the Liquid Mirrour, Sate down the Contemplative Prince, under the ſhade of a well-ſpread Almon Tree: On the other ſide the River was a Large tract of Meadow ground; where the Herds-Men and Shepherds uſed to feed their Wanton Herds, &amp; Quiet Flocks; On that ſide by a Covert of Mirtles were ſeated Melander and Florius (two of the Paſtoral Fraternity) unboſoming each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Rural Cares; the ſhade of their Mirtle Obſcured Eraſtus from their View, which gave him the better opportunity to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Diſcourſe; the Theam whereof was ſuch as is uſual to Shepherds; for the Cruelty of Amarillis, the coyneſs of Chloris, the diſdain of Phillis, the Severity of Paſtora, and the Inconſtancy of Serina; had ſet their Enamour'd Captives Hearts on akeing, their Breaſts a panting; their Eyes a Mourning; had filled their diſcourſe with rueful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, whilſt the Neighbouring Woods
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:51812:76"/> and Rivers were made acquainted with their Piteous Lamentations. But above all, the ſtrange humour of Prunella (the Idol of Florius) may not be unpleaſant to Interlard this dull Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>My Melander (ſaid he, after he had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged a Volley of Sighs, and made three or four Grimmaces) Thou knowſt with how great Conſtancy I have ever ſerved the Lovely Prunella; thou art witneſs of my cares for her, and the Care that (for her ſake) I had for her Flock, not a Sore Sheep but I dreſs'd, not a Straggling Lamb, but I fetcht home, when ſhe ſigh'd, I ſigh'd; and when ſhe ſmiled, it lookt like the ſweet ſimpering of a Roſey Morning; when ſhe ſlept, Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy would ſhut up my Eyelids as truely as if the null god of ſlumber had done it himſelf; when ſhe Sang, I could not forbear playing on my Pipe, and never were its Notes ſo pleaſant as when tuned to the Melodious key of her Voice. What ſhall I ſay Melander? I have bin thus her Slave above theſe Seaven Years; I have no Ioyes, but hers; nor no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſires, but with Submiſſion to the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Prunella? Iuſt after our laſt Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhearing. I ſent her a Copy of my thoughts in Rythme, and I fancy they were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible neither; but would you think it? She anſwered them with that Intollerable diſdain, as would have broke a Heart of Milſtone.</p>
               <p>Prethee Florius (ſaid Melander) bleſs me with a little of thy Poetry; this is the firſt time I ever heard thou hadſt any gift that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:51812:77"/> way, but what will not Love. Ah! the Charmes of All-Inſpiring Love, what can't they do? Let the Dull old Bards talk of the Efficacy of their Watery Helicon, one drop of that Nectar that flows from the Lips of Prunella, will do more than an Ocean of that cold and melancholly Liquor: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dear Florius, hide not the ſatisfaction of this Chiming humour from thy faithful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident Melander. Well (ſaid Florius) I will not conceal them from thee, if thou wilt but aſſiſt in anſwering her contemptful Lines: which Melander conſenting to, Florius repeated him the Lines, which you are like to hear.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>When firſt I ſaw thee, thou didſt ſweetly Play</l>
                  <l>The Gentle Theif, and ſtol'ſt my Heart Away:</l>
                  <l>Give't me again, or I will Swear thou art,</l>
                  <l>A ſweet-Face't Creature with a double Heart.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Piſh, Piſh (quoth Melander) theſe are as old as Pauls; but however, it argues a very good memory, that you ſo well retain them beſides, they are very pat to the purpoſe. Ay (quoth Florius) I think ſo and much too good for the Abuſive anſwer ſhe returned, which I will ſhew you, that you may read them. Melander opening the Paper, found theſe Lines.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sitting at Shiting, I receiv'd your Letter,</l>
                  <l>Peruſing it, I Sh—t the better;</l>
                  <l>And finding it ſo full of Wit,</l>
                  <l>The more I Read, the more I Sh—t.</l>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:51812:77"/>
                  <l>The place whereon their grew no Graſs,</l>
                  <l>Your Letter came Juſt fit to wipe mine Ar—</l>
               </q>
               <p>This is Comical indeed! (ſaid Melander) would ever an inſulting Carryon thus abuſe the Faithful Addreſſes of her Bigotted Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd? But it is e'en too good for the Dotard Florius; well, trouble not thy ſelf! thou ſhalt have a draught of my thoughts concerning this Idol of thine; but firſt for an anſwer to her Scurrillity, which methinks might run well enough in theſe words.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O my Pretty Fool,</l>
                  <l>How glad am I it gave thee ſo good a Stool;</l>
                  <l>What e're it coſt me, I will have</l>
                  <l>This Epitaph ſet on thy Grave.</l>
                  <l>Beauty fair, this Tomb doth hide;</l>
                  <l>Shiting ſhe Liv'd, Shiting ſhe Died;</l>
                  <l>Who e'er he be, that paſſeth by</l>
                  <l>The Place wherein her Bones do lye,</l>
                  <l>Can do her no greater Honour,</l>
                  <l>Than to come and Piſs, and Sh—t upon her.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Dear Melander! I con thee thanks with all my heart, cryed the almoſt Tranſported Florius, by Venus thou haſt claw'd her ofe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a witneſs, now am I reſolved to ſend her this Epitaph as a laſt farewel of Flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us's Love, and bury my Inclinations under the ſame beſhitten marble; for after this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable defiance, ſhe ſhall never more make a Nokes of her Humble Servant Florius. But now ſweet Melander (continued he) let me have a Coppy of thy thoughts concerning her,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:51812:78"/> as thou didſt promiſe: which Melander ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly gave him after this ſort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If we agree with thoſe that affirm Phancy to be the Creator of Beauty, as the Poet hath it,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>If I Phancy Black or Blew,</l>
                     <l>Or any other Hue,</l>
                     <l>That Phancy doth a Beauty make.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Should we be of this Opinion? I know no reaſon but your</hi> Prunella <hi>may paſs for a Beauty; but if we believe, that there is a certain proportion, and regularity of parts, together with a mixture of ſomwhat called Complexion, that are neceſſary ingredients to the compoſing a Handſom woman; then I aſſure you I can by no means allow your quondam Miſtreſs to put in for any ſhare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the many Pretenders to handſom Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for (how much ſoever you adore her) her eyes look a croſs, and one of them is big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the other by above halfe an inch like a Tumblers; her noſe looks like a Cloak Button ſet in the midſt of her face; and her mouth is drawn up to one ear on one ſide, and the other Cheek Stuft out with a Tennis Ball; her breath ſmells much like as her Tombſtone muſt, if there be any Charm in the Epitaph I gave you: And for her Complexion, I can no better deſcribe it, than a friend of mine did by a Miſtris of his, who
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:51812:78"/> deſired him to paint what kind of Wife he could wiſh;</hi> Madam, <hi>replyed he, If you would ſit to draw it by, it muſt be thus,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Eyes muſt be Braſs,</l>
                     <l>Her Lips of Pearl,</l>
                     <l>Teeth as green as Graſs,</l>
                     <l>Hair like a Squirrel,</l>
                     <l>Her Noſe of Rubie,</l>
                     <l>Her Brow of Steel,</l>
                     <l>Her Cheeks ſhould Blew be,</l>
                     <l>And her Neck Braziel.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Which Deſcription of his had its deſired Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, for it begat ſuch a diſtance in her, that he was never after troubled with her loathſome Importunities. At this they aroſe and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Flocks to the Fold, it being now grown towards Sun-ſet. The well-pleaſed Eraſtus that had paſſed many a ſmile dure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their divertive diſcourſe, returned to the Pallace, all the way, not a little admiring at the Innocent pleaſures of the Shepherds life; but moſt of all taken with the Witty Drollery of Melander.</p>
               <p>He could not forbear at Supper to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint his generous Hoſt with much of the diſcourſe he had heard; to whom the Noble Man replyed, that he had enquired concerning Melander, and underſtood him to be a Noble Britain, who for ſome private (but ſuppoſed Amorous Reaſon) ſpent his time amongſt the Shepherds in that diſguiſe.</p>
               <p>That night the Emperor gave order to have all things in readineſs by the next morning
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:51812:79"/> for the purſuing his Progreſs, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly he did, being well ſatisfied with the Temper, &amp; Entertainments of that Country; which accounted his preſence among them the greateſt of their Felicities; whilſt <hi>Long Live the beſt of Emperours,</hi> was the general Acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that filled the reſounding Air as he paſſed. He Iournied through Helvetia and Flanders to the Town of Donkirk, where he Imbark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Britain, then called Albion, and Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana, and through the Noble and Opulent Channel of the Thames, was brought atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a Fleet which the Britains had orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the purpoſe, to the Antient and Great Metropolis of London.</p>
               <p>In thoſe dayes had this Iſland purchaſed ſo great Eſteem among the Victorious Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, that they juſtly accounted it the faireſt Branch of the Imperial Laurel; and either the ever famous Eraſtus, Or ſome other Emperor beſtowed on that City the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Name of Auguſta, an Honor which proud Rome her ſelf could never attain to; no nor any of the Aſpiring Chambers of the Emperors.</p>
               <p>Eraſtus was infinitely ſatisfied with the Pomps of their Buildings, the Magnificence of their Treats, the prodigeous Wealth of their Merchants, the Fertillity of the Soil, affording ſo vaſt plenty to that prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Foreſt of People, that ſeemed as a World of themſelves, that it was a little difficult to reſolve whether theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or that of the Economy of their Laws
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:51812:79"/> the equallity of their Government; the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs of their Diſpoſitions, and the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity of their well-temper'd Souls, mainly drew the Affections of the Roman Emperor to this (then) Fortunate People. I have not come to incert the many Various wayes they endeavoured to manifeſt the Honor and happineſs they conceived in his preſence with them; Nor the many Statues, Medals, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, Inſcriptions, and vaſt Buildings the Emperor was at the expence of, to teſtifie the high Eſteem he had of them. This is largely done by other Hiſtorians. I have only place to incert two Diſticks; which either Eraſtus, or ſome other made in praiſe of a Rural Life; and to promiſe an account of his Marriage with an Engliſh Princeſs, and his return to Rome; with many various and pleaſant accidents in another Volum. But I muſt conclude with the Verſes, which were theſe,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Happy is the Country Life,</l>
                        <l>Bleſt with Content, good Health, and Eaſe,</l>
                        <l>Free from Factious Noiſe, and Strife,</l>
                        <l>We only Plot our ſelves to pleaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Peace of Mind's our dayes Delight,</l>
                        <l>And Love's our welcom dream at Night.</l>
                        <pb n="152" facs="tcp:51812:80"/>
                        <l>Hail green Fields, and ſhady Woods,</l>
                        <l>Hail Springs and Streams that ſtill run pure,</l>
                        <l>Natures Uncorrupted Goods,</l>
                        <l>Where Virtue only is ſecure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Free from Vice, VVe're free from Care;</l>
                        <l>Age is no Pain, nor Youth no Snare.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51812:80"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
